<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>reluctant criminologists</title>
<link>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Jon Brauer and Jake Day&#39;s blog and course materials.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.335</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Causation without Correlation?</title>
  <dc:creator>Jon Brauer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/empty-egg-dag3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Empty Easter egg, or countervailing causation?</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="sec-ladder" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-ladder">Thinking up the ladder of causation</h2>
<p>I have taught a version of my undergraduate introductory course on theories of crime and deviance (CJUS-P 200 at <a href="https://criminaljustice.indiana.edu/index.html">Indiana University</a>) nearly every semester for the past 15 years and across three different universities. In each of those courses, my second lecture has always been devoted to teaching <em>principles of causality</em>.</p>
<p>I start that segment with a thought question and class discussion about what it means to say that something “causes” something else. Most of the time, students start with correlational descriptions of causality, such as “X causes Y means that when X changes, Y tends to change.” Such answers are what <a href="http://bayes.cs.ucla.edu/WHY/">Pearl &amp; Mackenzie</a> refer to as a “rung one” observation on the <a href="https://blogs.kcl.ac.uk/behaviouralinsights/2020/07/07/why-you-should-read-the-book-of-why/">ladder of causation</a>. In contrast, it is much rarer for students to intuit with minimal prompting a <a href="https://engineeringideas.substack.com/i/47016069/counterfactuals">counterfactual</a> or “rung three” description of causality, such as “if X caused Y, then Y might not have changed if X had not changed.”</p>
<p>At first glance, this may be a bit unexpected. We seem to engage in counterfactual thinking naturally, as it appears central to <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/counterfactuals/">imagination and rational agency</a>. Pearl and Mackenzie go so far as to claim that the ability to use counterfactual thinking to make “explanation-seeking inferences reliably and repeatably” is what “most distinguishes human from animal intelligence, as well as from model-blind versions of AI and machine learning” (<a href="https://www.basicbooks.com/titles/judea-pearl/the-book-of-why/9780465097616/">2018</a>, p.33). Moreover, the belief that randomization in controlled experiments offers a valid mechanism for making causal inferences relies upon counterfactual reasoning about potential outcomes; these counterfactual justifications underlying classical statistics were proposed by pioneers Jersey Neyman and Sir Ronald Fisher <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/causal-inference-for-statistics-social-and-biomedical-sciences/brief-history-of-the-potential-outcomes-approach-to-causal-inference/B8CEDDC08F0E0D6C577847F0CBE4E6A3">a century ago</a>! Meanwhile, principled counterfactual frameworks using potential outcomes to make causal inferences with observational data have been in use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubin_causal_model">since the 1970s</a> and represent arguably <a href="https://jech.bmj.com/content/76/11/960">the best approach to causal identification with observational data today</a>.</p>
<p>Yet, counterfactuals also <a href="https://www.inference.vc/causal-inference-3-counterfactuals/">are weird and can be difficult to comprehend</a>, particularly when using formal statistical notation. So, I still start with a discussion of the three basic criteria for establishing causal claims found in most sociology and criminology textbooks (correlation; nonspuriousness; temporal order). From there, I very briefly introduce students to some more advanced ideas, such as simple versus complex causality, causal chains, causal mechanisms and mediation, effect heterogeneity and moderation, and, of course, counterfactual causality. In doing so, I often tell students that, while they might know that correlation does not necessarily imply causation, they may be surprised to learn that <strong>causation may exist even in the absence of observed correlation</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-reasons" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-reasons">Causation without correlation</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/DALL-E_pop_art_style_portrait_painting_of_someone_very_confused3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Pop art portrait of someone very confused, by DALL-E</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>To say students are surprised by this claim is an understatement - many seem confused or downright skeptical when I state it. After all, didn’t we just discuss how a basic criteria for establishing that X causes Y is <em>observing a correlation</em> between X and Y? Anticipating this confusion, I provide an example involving multiple mediation.</p>
<p>In fact, there are a number of reasons why two variables, X &amp; Y, can be causally related despite the lack of an observed bivariate or conditional (partial) correlation between them that have nothing to do with multiple mediation. Many of these reasons involve a <em>failure to detect</em> a correlation where one is expected to exist due to an existing causal relationship (notice the counterfactual reasoning again?). Examples include poor measurement and insufficient statistical power of a test to detect an effect, or improper modeling of <a href="https://qr.ae/pvj4pD">nonlinear (e.g., parabolic) functional relationships</a>, or <a href="https://www.christopherspenn.com/2018/08/can-causation-exist-without-correlation/">sample selection bias</a>. Interestingly, it is possible to fail to observe a correlation between two variables even when in situations where there is nearly perfect functional causality (<a href="https://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/causation-without-correlation-is-possible/">see advanced example at end here</a>).</p>
<p>While it is certainly important to understand how and why we might sometimes fail to statistically detect a correlation between X &amp; Y where one might be causally expected, the example I use draws from a different situation in which one <em>would not even expect the existence of a statistical correlation</em> between X &amp; Y even with precise measurement, sufficient power, careful sampling, and so on, and despite a reasonable belief in the existence of causal processes or mechanisms connecting X &amp; Y. Examples of this situation might include counteracting direct and indirect effects or multiple countervailing mediators.</p>
<p>The statistical literature on mediation was particularly formative for my thinking on this topic. For example, consider the following excerpt from <a href="https://www.ln.edu.hk/mkt/staff/gcui/Hayes2009.pdf">Andrew Hayes’ (2009, p.413)</a> article, <em>Beyond Baron &amp; Kenny: Statistical Mediation Analysis in the New Millennium</em>, which was published around the time I first started teaching my theories of crime course and in the same year that I published <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1745-9125.2009.00164.x">my very first article</a>, which included a “test” of a mediation hypothesis using the old school <a href="https://davidakenny.net/cm/mediate.htm#BK">Baron &amp; Kenny method</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Can Effects that Don’t Exist be ‘Mediated’?<br>
<br> If a mediator is a variable, M, that is causally between X and Y and that <em>accounts at least in part for the association between X and Y</em>, then by definition X and Y must be associated in order for M to be a mediator of that effect. According to this logic, if there is no evidence that X affects Y, then how can X’s effect on Y be mediated and so what is the point of estimating indirect and direct effects? But it is possible for M to be causally between X and Y even if X and Y aren’t associated. In this case, some prefer to avoid the term <em>mediator</em> when describing M and instead refer simply to X’s indirect effect on Y through M…<br>
<br> The distinction between mediation and indirect effect is not always made by users of the Baron and Kenny method, who may prematurely end the hunt for evidence of indirect effects if there is no evidence that X and Y are associated. If the size of <em>c</em> [path coefficients] constrained the size of <em>a</em> and <em>b</em> and therefore their product, this logic would make sense. Unfortunately, no such constraints exist, and it is easy to show that the claim that X can’t affect Y indirectly in the absence of a detectable total effect is false.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this excerpt, Hayes first expresses the common sentiment that X &amp; Y must be correlated if they are causally connected through a mediator, then proceeds to inform us that this view has been debunked as a myth. Yet, despite this being a well-established fact in the mediation/indirect effect literature for many years, I was surprised to find very few accessible examples online to which I could point students and colleagues for a more detailed illustration of the type of situation I regularly describe to them. So, I did what any nerd who recently learned R would do - I simulated some data to help my students better visualize an example. Then, I thought that others also might be uninformed or confused about the issue, and here we are.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-ai">AI to the rescue?</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/DALL-E_person_climbing_mountain_to_seek_wisdom_from_computer_cartoon3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Cartoon person seeking wisdom from a computer oracle, by DALL-E</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Before transforming my simulation example for students into a blog entry, I sought the wisdom of the artificial intelligence oracle <a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt">ChatGPT</a>, thinking it might lead me to existing examples that I was missing. I realize that, at present, ChatGPT is not particularly <a href="https://medium.com/@vanillaxiangshuyang/let-us-talk-about-chatgpt-b4be68dd0da">well-suited for causal reasoning</a>, as <a href="https://twitter.com/yudapearl/status/1642780699953627137?s=20">Pearl himself has documented</a> and the AI oracle itself <a href="https://twitter.com/yudapearl/status/1641386266595033088?s=20">has humbly admitted</a>, though it also notes some ability to <a href="https://twitter.com/DrJimFan/status/1641111697971884034?s=20">extract, mimic, or make guesses from data containing information about causal relations</a>. Nonetheless, I asked the oracle: “Is it possible to have causation without correlation?”</p>
<p>For those interested in such things, I have included the full conversation with ChatGPT in the expandable link below.</p>
<details>
<summary>
Conversation with ChatGPT (4/5/2023, 12:20am)
</summary>
<style>
div.magma { background-color:#fddc9e80; border-radius: 5px; padding: 20px;}
</style>
<style>
div.limey { background-color:#d1e18980; border-radius: 5px; padding: 20px;}
</style>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> Is it possible to have causation without correlation?</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> Yes, it is possible to have causation without correlation. While causation and correlation are often related, they are not the same thing.</p>
<p>Correlation refers to a statistical relationship between two variables, where a change in one variable tends to be associated with a change in the other variable. However, correlation does not necessarily imply causation, because there could be other factors at play that influence both variables. For example, there is a correlation between the number of ice cream cones sold and the number of drownings each year, but this does not mean that ice cream causes drownings.</p>
<p>Causation, on the other hand, refers to a relationship where one event (the cause) brings about another event (the effect). A causal relationship can exist even if there is no correlation between the two variables, because the relationship is not dependent on a statistical pattern. For example, smoking causes lung cancer, but not everyone who smokes gets lung cancer, and not everyone with lung cancer smokes.</p>
<p>In summary, while correlation and causation are often linked, they are not the same thing, and it is possible to have causation without correlation.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> In your smoking example, if smoking causes lung cancer, wouldn’t there also be a statistical relationship (i.e., a correlation) between smoking and lung cancer? The statement that “not everyone who smokes gets lung cancer, and not everyone with lung cancer smokes” does not rule out the possibility (or the likelihood) of a statistical relationship - it only rules out the possibility of a perfect correlation.</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> You are correct that in the case of smoking causing lung cancer, there is typically a statistical relationship (i.e., a correlation) between smoking and lung cancer. In fact, smoking is one of the strongest risk factors for developing lung cancer, and studies have consistently shown a strong correlation between smoking and lung cancer.</p>
<p>My previous statement about not everyone who smokes getting lung cancer and not everyone with lung cancer smoking was intended to highlight the fact that while there is a strong correlation between smoking and lung cancer, it is not a perfect correlation. In other words, there are some people who smoke and do not develop lung cancer, and there are some people who develop lung cancer even though they have never smoked.</p>
<p>So while a correlation between smoking and lung cancer does exist, it is not a one-to-one relationship, and it is possible for some smokers to avoid lung cancer and for some non-smokers to develop lung cancer. However, this does not negate the fact that smoking is a significant risk factor for developing lung cancer, and the statistical relationship between the two remains strong.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> Yes, but the question was whether it is possible to have causation without correlation. You gave an example of causation with correlation.</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> You are correct, my apologies for any confusion. The smoking example I gave was indeed an example of causation with correlation.</p>
<p>To provide an example of causation without correlation, imagine a scenario where a scientist discovers that a specific gene mutation causes a rare disease that affects only a small portion of the population. In this case, there may not be a statistical relationship or correlation between the gene mutation and the disease in the general population, because the disease is so rare and the gene mutation is only found in a small portion of the population. However, there is a clear causal relationship between the gene mutation and the disease.</p>
<p>So, to answer the original question more accurately, it is possible to have causation without a statistically significant correlation between the two variables in the general population, as in the rare disease example described above.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> In that example, again, there is a correlation between the gene mutation and the disease. I did not ask about whether there could be causation without a statistically significant correlation - statistical significance depends on power of the test. So, in this causal example, if you had a sufficiently large sample, the correlation would also be detected, making it another example of causation with correlation.</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> You are correct, and I apologize for the confusion. In the scenario I described, there is indeed a correlation between the gene mutation and the rare disease, even though it may not be statistically significant in the general population due to the low prevalence of the disease.</p>
<p>It is true that statistical significance depends on the power of the test and the sample size, and it is possible that a correlation between two variables could become statistically significant with a larger sample size. Therefore, in this case, with a larger sample size, the correlation between the gene mutation and the rare disease would likely be detected, and it would be an example of causation with correlation.</p>
<p>Thank you for pointing out this mistake in my previous responses, and I hope this clarification is helpful.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> So, can you think of another example of causation without correlation that does not involve an insufficiently powered test for detecting correlation?</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> Yes, I can provide another example of causation without correlation that does not involve an insufficiently powered test for detecting correlation.</p>
<p>Consider the example of a person who takes a medication that causes a significant reduction in their symptoms of a medical condition. In this case, there is a clear causal relationship between taking the medication and the improvement in symptoms, but there may not be a statistical correlation between the two variables in the general population.</p>
<p>This lack of correlation could be due to a number of factors, such as individual differences in the severity or type of the medical condition, or differences in the dosage or timing of the medication. Additionally, the relationship between the medication and the symptoms could be confounded by other factors, such as the person’s diet, exercise habits, or stress levels.</p>
<p>So, in this scenario, while there may not be a statistically significant correlation between taking the medication and the improvement in symptoms in the general population, there is a clear causal relationship between the two variables in the individual person who experienced the improvement in symptoms.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> This example again leverages a lack of statistical significance, which I am unmoved by such arguments. For instance, here, there is causation and likely correlation - but the correlation is not detectable due to improper modeling due to issues like heterogeneity in the strength of the effect, confounding, poor measurement, or inadequately specifying dosage and time. Can you think of any other examples that are different from these?</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> Thank you for the feedback and clarification. I will provide another example of causation without correlation that is different from the previous examples.</p>
<p>Consider the example of a person who develops a fear of flying after experiencing a traumatic event on a plane, such as severe turbulence or an emergency landing. In this case, the traumatic event on the plane is the direct cause of the person’s fear of flying.</p>
<p>However, there may not be a statistical correlation between traumatic events on planes and the development of a fear of flying in the general population. This is because not everyone who experiences a traumatic event on a plane will develop a fear of flying, and some people may develop a fear of flying for other reasons unrelated to traumatic events.</p>
<p>Therefore, in this scenario, there is a clear causal relationship between the traumatic event on the plane and the person’s fear of flying, but there may not be a statistically significant correlation between the two variables in the general population.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> Interesting. If it was a singular event, then would there not be a perfect correlation between flight exposure and fear of flying since there are two data points (pre-exposure level of fear &amp; post-exposure levels of fear)? If it is not a singular event and there is some proportion of the population that develops fear of flying after exposure to flying, then again we are back to the rare genetic cause of disease example - with sufficient data, we would be able to detect this causally driven correlation in the population. Any other ideas?</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> You make a good point, and I apologize for any confusion. The example I provided may not be a good example of causation without correlation.</p>
<p>Another example of causation without correlation could be the case of a person who develops an allergic reaction to a specific food after consuming it for the first time. In this case, the food is the direct cause of the allergic reaction, but there may not be a statistically significant correlation between consuming the food and developing an allergic reaction in the general population.</p>
<p>This lack of correlation could be due to individual differences in genetics or immune system function, or differences in the amount or preparation of the food consumed. Additionally, the relationship between the food and the allergic reaction could be confounded by other factors, such as the person’s age or other underlying health conditions.</p>
<p>Therefore, in this scenario, while there may not be a statistically significant correlation between consuming the food and developing an allergic reaction in the general population, there is a clear causal relationship between the two variables in the individual person who experienced the allergic reaction.</p>
</div>
<div class="limey">
<p><strong><em>Jon Brauer</em></strong> <br> Again, this example seems to have a very similar logical structure and empirical implications of your previous examples. I am going to write a blog entry on causation without correlation that covers a different type of example. I will share the idea with you in case it helps you answer questions like this. Another reason there might be causation without correlation is that an exposure affects multiple mechanisms that have countervailing effects on an outcome. For instance, the exposure might be causally related to the mediators and correlated with the mediators, but and the mediators are causally related to the outcome and correlated with the outcome but in opposite directions, thereby resulting in a null (negated or cancelled out) correlation in the population. There would still be causation, though, since one could imagine intervening on one mediating pathway to hold it constant, then the exposure would cause change the outcome - and be correlated with the outcome - through the other mediating pathway. Have you encountered any examples like this before?</p>
</div>
<div class="magma">
<p><strong><em>ChatGPT</em></strong> <br> Thank you for sharing your idea. That is a very interesting perspective on causation without correlation, and it makes sense that an exposure affecting multiple mechanisms could result in countervailing effects on an outcome, leading to a null correlation in the population.</p>
<p>I have not encountered this specific example before, but I can see how it could arise in situations where there are complex and interrelated causal pathways between an exposure and an outcome. For example, in a study investigating the effects of a particular medication on a disease outcome, the medication may affect multiple biological pathways that have opposing effects on the disease outcome. As a result, the overall correlation between medication use and disease outcome may be null or weak, even though the medication is causing changes in the underlying biological pathways and ultimately influencing the disease outcome.</p>
<p>I hope this example helps to provide a different perspective on causation without correlation, and thank you for bringing up this interesting topic.</p>
</div>
</details>
<p>To its credit, ChatGPT recognized the possibility of causation without correlation. However, it primarily provided examples where causation exists and correlation would be expected to exist but, for reasons such as event rarity, shoddy measurement, or insufficiently powered tests, researchers are unable to detect an actually existing (i.e., nonzero) correlation. Again, what I wanted was an example where causality exists, yet where we would <em>not</em> expect to detect a correlation (e.g., we might expect <em>r</em>=0).</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-dependence" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-dependence">Causation <em>does</em> require statistical dependence</h2>
<p>One final point of clarification before getting to an example. The basic criteria are not really wrong. Causation involves <strong>statistical dependence</strong> between X and (mechanisms of) Y, and statistical dependence may exist despite a lack of observed linear correlation. I think it may be easier for some people to understand how this might happen for methodological reasons (e.g., imprecise measures; insufficient data; mispecified model) than it is to understand how this might happen for theoretical reasons. Counterfactual reasoning can help; so can <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1745-9133.12027">causal models</a> or <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggdag/vignettes/intro-to-dags.html">directed acyclic graphs (DAGs)</a>.</p>
<p>For instance, you might be wondering if it is really useful or accurate to say that X causes Y if there is no (total) statistical dependence between X &amp; Y - that is, if (in some populations or samples comprised of units with particular levels of key variables) Y does not reliably change after X changes. Yes, I think so! To understand why, it is helpful to consider an example, to rely on causal models, and to engage in counterfactual thinking. There are many possible examples; for simplicity, let’s imagine only four variables - X, M1, M2, and Y - that are causally related like so:</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(tidyverse)</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(ggplot2)</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(patchwork)</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(psych)</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># library(devtools)</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># install_github("jtextor/dagitty/r")</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(dagitty)</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">XYdag <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">dagitty</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"dag{</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">  X -&gt; M1 -&gt; Y</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">  X -&gt; M2 -&gt; Y</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">   }"</span>) </span>
<span id="cb1-13"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coordinates</span>(XYdag) <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">list</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-14">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">X=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">M1=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">M2=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Y=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>),</span>
<span id="cb1-15">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">X=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">M1=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">M2=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Y=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>) )</span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">plot</span>(XYdag)</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>In this hypothetical example, imagine that increasing or “dialing up the knob” on X causes an increase in both M1 and M2. Imagine also that increasing or dialing up M1 causes an <em>increase</em> in Y, whereas an increase in M2 causes a <em>decrease</em> in Y of comparable magnitude in the opposite direction (i.e., countervailing indirect effects). So, when we dial up X, we also causally up M1 and M2, which in turn equivalently dials Y up (through M1) and down (through M2) - meaning Y does not change when X changes despite changes in mediators.</p>
<p>So, you might still be wondering whether it is reasonable to describe this situation as one in which X <em>causes</em> Y, or whether this is an example of <strong>causation</strong> without (XY) correlation. Again, I say YES! To understand why, let’s use counterfactual reasoning. I want you to further imagine that we identify a way to intervene on the X -&gt; M1 -&gt; Y pathway. For instance, perhaps we design an intervention to mitigate or disrupt the X -&gt; M1 causal effect so that, when we dial up X, M1 no longer subsequently increases or it increases to a much lesser degree; that is, our intervention allows us to hold constant the level of M1 following a change in X, thereby negating the positive indirect effect of X on Y through M1. Now in this counterfactual situation, when we dial up X, what would happen to Y? It would change in a causally predictable way: If X increases, Y would decrease due to the negative indirect effect of X on Y through M2!</p>
<p>I hope this abstract example helps illustrate why, without the proper causal model guiding our statistical modeling decisions and interpretations of data, it is easy to fail to observe statistical dependence where it exists (and vice versa) and then to incorrectly infer a lack of causality (or its presence) from the absence (or presence) of observed correlation. To avoid such traps, what we need is to understand theoretically how and why X is related to Y - e.g., by creating a <em>causal diagram</em> that accurately depicts the causal relationship(s) between these variables and by using counterfactual reasoning. Once we identify the correct causal model generating the data, then we can model the data in a way that permits us to observe statistical dependence and identify the causal effect(s) of X on Y. In short, we really need to understand <strong>theory</strong>, or logical statements of the causal relations between concepts, to properly model and interpret our data.</p>
<p>With all that said, it can be difficult to grasp abstract examples, and it may be tempting to wonder whether such situations really exist in our world. So, let’s draw inspiration from a real study in criminology to add meat to the abstract bones of our example.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-sescrim" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-sescrim">Example from criminology</h2>
<p>Specifically, we will draw inspiration from Bradley Wright and colleagues’ (1999) <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1745-9125.1999.tb00483.x">paper in Criminology</a> entitled “Reconsidering the relationship between SES and delinquency: Causation but not correlation.” Seems fitting, eh?</p>
<p>The basic idea is this: There is a long history of debates over the SES-delinquency relationship. Some theories specifically posit a negative causal relationship (i.e., low SES -&gt; high delinquency), yet observational research has documented inconsistent patterns (e.g., weak negative, nonexistent, or even positive relationships). Wright and colleagues argue that this state of affairs may be due to SES simultaneously having positive and negative causal effects on crime through countervailing mechanisms. Together, the positive and negative effects of these mechanisms may generally offset each other in many survey datasets, which might result in observing a lack of any bivariate correlation between SES and delinquency (i.e., “total effect” estimate = 0) and/or inconsistent partial correlations (i.e., variable conditional direct effect etimates) depending on which mechanisms are included or excluded from researchers’ statistical models.</p>
<p>We will illustrate how something like this might happen using simulated data. Specifically, we will simulate data for <em>parental SES</em>, <em>child delinquency</em>, and two potential countervailing mechanisms - <em>financial strain</em> and <em>perceived risk of detection</em> of delinquent behaviors. In our simulated example, we will assume parental SES does not directly cause child delinquency and that it indirectly causes child delinquency through both mediating mechanisms. Additionally, we will assume that the causal effects of Parental SES on financial strain and perceived risk of detection are equal in magnitude and that the causal effect of financial strain on delinquency is equal in magnitude yet opposite in direction, such that both indirect or mediated effects offset one another. Below is a directed acyclic graph, or DAG, of this simple causal structure.</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">SESdag <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">dagitty</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"dag{</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">  SES -&gt; Strain -&gt; Delinquency</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">  SES -&gt; Risk -&gt; Delinquency</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4"><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">   }"</span>) </span>
<span id="cb2-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coordinates</span>(SESdag) <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">list</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-6">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">SES=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Strain=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Risk=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Delinquency=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>),</span>
<span id="cb2-7">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">SES=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Strain=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Risk=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Delinquency=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>) )</span>
<span id="cb2-8"></span>
<span id="cb2-9"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">plot</span>(SESdag)</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Now let’s simulate some data. In doing so, note we round data drawn from continuous (i.e., normal &amp; Poisson) distributions to integers; this adds a bit of noise to the data yet also makes our variables more comparable to the types of ordinal, Likert-type measures we see in our field.</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># X = Parental SES</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Y = Child delinquent behavior</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># F = Mediatior through which high Parent SES might decrease delinquency - e.g., less financial (S)train</span></span>
<span id="cb3-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># P = Mediators through which high Parent SES increase delinquency - e.g., lower perceived (R)isk of detection</span></span>
<span id="cb3-5"></span>
<span id="cb3-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Strain -&gt; Delinquency &lt;- Risk </span></span>
<span id="cb3-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Strain &lt;- SES -&gt; Risk</span></span>
<span id="cb3-8"></span>
<span id="cb3-9"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">set.seed</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1138</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-10">n <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1000</span></span>
<span id="cb3-11"></span>
<span id="cb3-12"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># McElreath method (p.153)</span></span>
<span id="cb3-13"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># SES &lt;- rnorm(n)</span></span>
<span id="cb3-14"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Strain &lt;- rnorm(n,SES)</span></span>
<span id="cb3-15"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Risk &lt;- rnorm(n,SES)</span></span>
<span id="cb3-16"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Delinquency &lt;- rnorm(n,Strain-Risk)</span></span>
<span id="cb3-17"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># </span></span>
<span id="cb3-18"></span>
<span id="cb3-19"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/10691898.2020.1752859</span></span>
<span id="cb3-20"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">set.seed</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1138</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-21">n <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1000</span></span>
<span id="cb3-22">SES <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">round</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">rnorm</span>(n),<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">digits=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-23">Strain <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">round</span>(<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">5</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">rnorm</span>(n),<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">digits=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-24">Risk <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">round</span>(<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">5</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">rnorm</span>(n),<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">digits=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-25">Delinquency <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">round</span>(.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">5</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>Strain <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">5</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>Risk <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">rpois</span>(n,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>),<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">digits=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-26"></span>
<span id="cb3-27">simdata <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">tibble</span>(SES, Strain, Risk, Delinquency)</span>
<span id="cb3-28">simdata <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> simdata <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">mutate</span>(</span>
<span id="cb3-29">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">Delinquency =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ifelse</span>(Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>, Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span>, Delinquency)</span>
<span id="cb3-30">)</span>
<span id="cb3-31"></span>
<span id="cb3-32">simdata</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code># A tibble: 1,000 × 4
     SES Strain  Risk Delinquency
   &lt;dbl&gt;  &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;dbl&gt;       &lt;dbl&gt;
 1    -1      1     0           2
 2    -1     -1     0           0
 3     0      1     1           2
 4     0     -1     0           0
 5    -1      0     1           0
 6    -1      1     0           2
 7     2     -1    -1           1
 8    -1      0    -1           4
 9     0      0    -2           2
10     1      0    -1           4
# … with 990 more rows</code></pre>
</div>
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1">SESplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> simdata <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_histogram</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>SES, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>..density..),</span>
<span id="cb5-3">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#1fa187"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fill=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#4ac16d"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">7</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-4">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">position=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"identity"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb5-5">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">breaks =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">seq</span>(<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">by =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-7">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb5-8">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb5-9">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-10">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Parental SES"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">NULL</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-11"></span>
<span id="cb5-12">Strainplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> simdata <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-13">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_histogram</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>Strain, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>..density..),</span>
<span id="cb5-14">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#1fa187"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fill=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#4ac16d"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">7</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-15">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">position=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"identity"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb5-16">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">breaks =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">seq</span>(<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">by =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-17">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-18">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb5-19">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb5-20">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-21">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Financial strain"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">NULL</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-22"></span>
<span id="cb5-23">Riskplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> simdata <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-24">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_histogram</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>Risk, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>..density..),</span>
<span id="cb5-25">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#1fa187"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fill=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#4ac16d"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">7</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-26">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">position=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"identity"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb5-27">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">breaks =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">seq</span>(<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">by =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-28">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-29">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb5-30">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb5-31">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-32">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Perceived risk of detection"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">NULL</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-33"></span>
<span id="cb5-34">Delqplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> simdata <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-35">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_histogram</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>Delinquency, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>..density..),</span>
<span id="cb5-36">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#1fa187"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fill=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#4ac16d"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">7</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-37">                 <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">position=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"identity"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-38">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb5-39">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb5-40">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb5-41">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb5-42">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Child delinquency"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">NULL</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-43"></span>
<span id="cb5-44"></span>
<span id="cb5-45">SESplot <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Strainplot <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Riskplot <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Delqplot</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="sec-bivar" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-bivar">Bivariate correlation</h3>
<p>Let’s examine the bivariate correlations between our simulated variables.</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># https://r-coder.com/correlation-plot-r/  </span></span>
<span id="cb6-2"></span>
<span id="cb6-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">pairs.panels</span>(simdata,</span>
<span id="cb6-4">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">smooth =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">FALSE</span>,      <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, draws loess smooths</span></span>
<span id="cb6-5">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">scale =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">FALSE</span>,      <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, scales the correlation text font</span></span>
<span id="cb6-6">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">density =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>,     <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, adds density plots and histograms</span></span>
<span id="cb6-7">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">ellipses =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">FALSE</span>,    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, draws ellipses</span></span>
<span id="cb6-8">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">method =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"pearson"</span>, <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Correlation method (also "spearman" or "kendall")</span></span>
<span id="cb6-9">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">pch =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">21</span>,           <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># pch symbol</span></span>
<span id="cb6-10">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">lm =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>,         <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, plots linear fit rather than the LOESS (smoothed) fit</span></span>
<span id="cb6-11">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">cor =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>,         <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, reports correlations</span></span>
<span id="cb6-12">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">jiggle =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">FALSE</span>,     <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, data points are jittered</span></span>
<span id="cb6-13">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">factor =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>,         <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Jittering factor</span></span>
<span id="cb6-14">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">hist.col =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>,       <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Histograms color</span></span>
<span id="cb6-15">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">stars =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>,       <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, adds significance level with stars</span></span>
<span id="cb6-16">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">ci =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>)          <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># If TRUE, adds confidence intervals</span></span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>As the pairs plot shows, there is virtually no correlation between SES and delinquency (<em>r</em> = -0.01). However, SES is negatively correlated with both mediators - financial strain (<em>r</em> = -0.43) and perceived risk (<em>r</em> = -0.40). Additionally, the mediator-delinquency correlations are similar in magnitude but opposite in direction (<em>r</em> = 0.30 for financial strain; <em>r</em> = -0.35 for perceived risk).</p>
<p>Given this, if we estimate a linear model<sup>1</sup> regressing delinquency on SES without the mediators, we should see another near-zero association between SES and delinquency because this model essentially reproduces the bivariate correlation (with a partially standardized beta coefficient). This means the <strong>total effect</strong> of SES - its direct effect plus all indirect effects through other mechanisms like financial strain and perceived risk, all combined - is estimated to be virtually zero (<em>b</em> = -0.01, se = 0.04). Thus, either SES has no direct or indirect causal effects on delinquency, or SES has direct and/or indirect causal effects on delinquency but we have failed to adequately identify it with our statistical model (and with the assumed causal model underlying it). For instance, perhaps the causal effect is non-linear, with positive and negative effects on delinquency at different levels of SES that average out to a null total effect. Or, perhaps SES has countervailing indirect effets through different mediating mechanisms and, together, the mediators offset each other to result in no total causal effect.</p>
<p>Of course, we know this last explanation is the true data generating process here because we simulated the data accordingly! However, in real-world data analysis, if you were to observe no correlation between two variables, you now know that it is unwise to immediately assume that there is no causal relationship between them.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-lm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-lm">Linear regressions</h3>
<p>The scatterplot and regression line from our bivariate linear regression model again illustrates the lack of total association between our simulated SES and delinqueny variables.<sup>2</sup></p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb7" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb7-1">lm1a <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">lm</span>(Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">~</span> SES, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">data=</span>simdata)</span>
<span id="cb7-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># summary(lm1a)</span></span>
<span id="cb7-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">summary</span>(lm1a)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>coefficients[,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>]</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>               Estimate Std. Error
(Intercept)  1.09914632 0.03855249
SES         -0.01125514 0.03849479</code></pre>
</div>
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb9" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb9-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># plot(simdata$SES, simdata$Delinquency)</span></span>
<span id="cb9-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># abline(lm1a)</span></span>
<span id="cb9-3"></span>
<span id="cb9-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;">#equation for delinquency regression line  </span></span>
<span id="cb9-5">eqY1a<span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">=</span><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;">function</span>(x){</span>
<span id="cb9-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1a)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>x <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1a)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb9-7">  }</span>
<span id="cb9-8"></span>
<span id="cb9-9">lmYplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>(simdata,<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>Delinquency,<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>SES)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb9-10">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_jitter</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">shape=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">21</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">width=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">height=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb9-11">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">stat_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fun=</span>eqY1a, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">geom=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"line"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;">1.5</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb9-12">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb9-13">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb9-14">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb9-15">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb9-16">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"SES"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Delinquency"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb9-17">lmYplot</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Now, let’s estimate a linear model regressing delinquency on SES and include <em>both mediators</em> as predictors in the model as well and then plot the regression line (with mediators set at their mean values). Once again, we should see a near-zero association between SES and delinquency, but for very different reasons this time. In this model, we are estimating what is commonly referred to as the <strong>direct effect</strong> of SES after stratifying on (aka, adjusting for) any potential indirect effects through financial strain and perceived risk mechanisms. Of course, we simulated our data in such a way that there would be no direct causal effect of SES on delinquency in our simulated data and, after including both mechanisms in the model, we accurately estimate virtually no direct effect of SES on delinquency (<em>b</em> = -0.03, se = 0.04). Hence, this plot looks comparable to the bivariate one above.</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb10" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb10-1">lm1b <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">lm</span>(Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">~</span> SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Strain <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Risk, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">data=</span>simdata)</span>
<span id="cb10-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># summary(lm1b)</span></span>
<span id="cb10-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">summary</span>(lm1b)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>coefficients[,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>]</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>               Estimate Std. Error     t value      Pr(&gt;|t|)
(Intercept)  1.07938412 0.03338240  32.3339287 2.126993e-157
SES         -0.02905861 0.03980686  -0.7299899  4.655680e-01
Strain       0.38859596 0.03290744  11.8087577  3.274331e-30
Risk        -0.43975564 0.03164821 -13.8951191  2.980525e-40</code></pre>
</div>
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb12" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb12-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># plot(simdata$SES, simdata$Delinquency)</span></span>
<span id="cb12-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># abline(lm1b)</span></span>
<span id="cb12-3"></span>
<span id="cb12-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;">#equation for delinquency regression line in model with both mediators at means  </span></span>
<span id="cb12-5">eqY1b<span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">=</span><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;">function</span>(x){</span>
<span id="cb12-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1b)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>x <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1b)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>] <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb12-7">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1b)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">mean</span>(simdata<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>Strain) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1b)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">mean</span>(simdata<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>Risk)</span>
<span id="cb12-8">  }</span>
<span id="cb12-9"></span>
<span id="cb12-10">lmYplot2 <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>(simdata,<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>Delinquency,<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>SES)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb12-11">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_jitter</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">shape=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">21</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">width=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">height=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb12-12">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">stat_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fun=</span>eqY1b, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">geom=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"line"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;">1.5</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb12-13">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb12-14">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb12-15">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb12-16">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb12-17">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"SES"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Delinquency"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb12-18">lmYplot2</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Note that this model above also estimates a positive effect of financial strain (<em>b</em> = 0.39, se = 0.03) and a negative effect of perceived risk (<em>b</em> = -0.44, se = 0.03) on delinquency. So, we might conclude that these theoretical mechanisms are related to delinquency as expected. But how would we know SES has indirect causal effects on delinquency through these mechanisms - i.e., that these variables <em>mediate</em> the SES-delinquency relationship? Well, we could estimate additional models regressing each mediator on SES; if SES predicts each mediator (which we know it does in our simulated data) and if each mediator predicts delinquency then, with certain strong assumptions in place (e.g., no exposure-mediator interaction and no unmeasured confounding of any paths; see <a href="https://www.publichealth.columbia.edu/research/population-health-methods/causal-mediation">here</a>, <a href="https://datacolada.org/103">here</a>, and <a href="https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/tyler-vanderweele/tools-and-tutorials/">here</a>), we can infer indirect causal effects of SES on delinquency. This is essentially the logic behind the classic <a href="https://davidakenny.net/cm/mediate.htm#BK">Baron &amp; Kenny method</a>. We can also extend this logic to test for and estimate the magnitude and confidence intervals around such indirect effects through each specific mediator.<sup>3</sup></p>
</section>
<section id="sec-trap" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-trap">Springing the causal trap</h3>
<p>But without jumping ahead to mediation tests, what would have happened if we had failed to specify the appropriate causal model ahead of time and, as a result, we mistakenly included <em>only one mediator</em> in the model with SES predicting delinquency? Let’s add financial strain to the model and exclude perceived risk from the model, then see what happens.</p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb13" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb13-1">lm1c <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">lm</span>(Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">~</span> SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> Strain, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">data=</span>simdata)</span>
<span id="cb13-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># summary(lm1c)</span></span>
<span id="cb13-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">summary</span>(lm1c)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>coefficients[,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>]</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>             Estimate Std. Error   t value
(Intercept) 1.0982531 0.03642628 30.150019
SES         0.1790345 0.04027868  4.444895
Strain      0.3951323 0.03593409 10.996029</code></pre>
</div>
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb15" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb15-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># plot(simdata$SES, simdata$Delinquency)</span></span>
<span id="cb15-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># abline(lm1c)</span></span>
<span id="cb15-3"></span>
<span id="cb15-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;">#equation for delinquency regression line in model with one mediator (at its mean)  </span></span>
<span id="cb15-5">eqY1c<span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">=</span><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;">function</span>(x){</span>
<span id="cb15-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1c)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span>x <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1c)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>] <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb15-7">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">coef</span>(lm1c)[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">3</span>]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">*</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">mean</span>(simdata<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">$</span>Strain) </span>
<span id="cb15-8">  }</span>
<span id="cb15-9"></span>
<span id="cb15-10">lmYplot3 <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ggplot</span>(simdata,<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span>Delinquency,<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span>SES)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb15-11">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">geom_jitter</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">alpha=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">shape=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">21</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">width=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">height=</span>.<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">2</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb15-12">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">stat_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">fun=</span>eqY1c, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">geom=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"line"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">color=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"#009E73"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">size=</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;">1.5</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb15-13">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme_minimal</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> </span>
<span id="cb15-14">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">theme</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.text.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>(),  </span>
<span id="cb15-15">        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">axis.ticks.y=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">element_blank</span>()</span>
<span id="cb15-16">        ) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb15-17">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">x=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"SES"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">y=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Delinquency"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb15-18">lmYplot3</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Uh oh. Suddenly, our model estimates a <em>positive</em> effect of SES on delinquency! Why?! Well, since we stratified on (adjusted for) financial strain, we essentially removed SES’s indirect effect on delinquency that operates through financial strain from our causal estimate. However, since we simulated these data, we know that SES also has an indirect effect on delinquency through perceived risk that is excluded from our model. So, the positive causal estimate of SES on delinquency in this model (<em>b</em> = 0.18, se = 0.04) reflects any direct effects of SES on delinquency (which we set to equal “0” in our simulation) and any indirect effects of SES on delinquency through unmeasured mediators - in this case, through perceived risk. We know that, in our simulated example, SES increases delinquency by reducing perceived risk of detection among those with high SES - that is, SES has <em>a positive indirect causal effect</em> on delinquency through perceived risk. Likewise, if we stratify on financial strain, thereby adjusting our estimate for this other known mediator, we are left with a positive estimate of the net causal effect of SES on delinquency (which we know is through perceived risk).</p>
<p>This should help illustrate an important point about so-called <strong>direct effect</strong> estimates - they are not really estimating “direct” effects at all. Rather, like bivariate correlation and regression coefficients, they are simply descriptive statistics that summarize the <strong>total</strong> effect of a predictor (SES) on an outcome (delinquency) through any and all unmeasured mechanisms.</p>
<p>This is an essential point. Imagine we were analyzing real non-simulated observational data and, after including measures of known mediating mechanisms (e.g., financial strain; perceived risk) in our model, we observed no association or “direct effect” of SES on delinquency (like in our second model <code>lm1b</code> above). In that situation, it is possible that there are no other mediating mechanisms through which SES might cause delinquency. However, it is also possible that there are additional unmeasured mechanisms that, combined, offset each other to result in a near-zero total remaining causal effect!</p>
<p>Moreover, bivariate correlations and partial regression coefficients also may be biased by effects of other unmeasured sources of confounding as well. In our simulation, we made a strong simplifying assumption that there were no such unmeasured sources of confounding and that we had identified all relevant mechanisms. However, with real data, such assumptions often are highly implausible. Hence, if one cares about causal effects of a variable (SES) on an outcome (delinquency) - total, indirect, or otherwise - then it is essential to identify the appropriate causal model and then to include (or exclude) variables as appropriate to accurately estimate the causal effect of interest. One cannot simply let the data speak.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/datacantspeak2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Data cannot speak meme</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="sec-mediate" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-mediate">Simple mediation tests</h3>
<p>Finally, let’s illustrate a simple test of the indirect effect of SES on delinquency using <code>mediate()</code> from the psych package.<sup>4</sup></p>
<div class="cell">
<details>
<summary>Show code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb16" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb16-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">mediate</span>(Delinquency <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">~</span> SES <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> (Strain) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> (Risk), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">data =</span> simdata, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">n.iter =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">10000</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">%&gt;%</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">print</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">short =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">TRUE</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png" class="img-fluid" width="672"></p>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>
Mediation/Moderation Analysis 
Call: mediate(y = Delinquency ~ SES + (Strain) + (Risk), data = simdata, 
    n.iter = 10000)

The DV (Y) was  Delinquency . The IV (X) was  SES . The mediating variable(s) =  Strain Risk .

Total effect(c) of  SES  on  Delinquency  =  -0.01   S.E. =  0.04  t  =  -0.29  df=  998   with p =  0.77
Direct effect (c') of  SES  on  Delinquency  removing  Strain Risk  =  -0.03   S.E. =  0.04  t  =  -0.73  df=  996   with p =  0.47
Indirect effect (ab) of  SES  on  Delinquency  through  Strain Risk   =  0.02 
Mean bootstrapped indirect effect =  0.02  with standard error =  0.03  Lower CI =  -0.04    Upper CI =  0.08
R = 0.5 R2 = 0.25   F = 112.47 on 3 and 996 DF   p-value:  3.83e-79 

 To see the longer output, specify short = FALSE in the print statement or ask for the summary</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>As before, these models estimate a near-zero total effect (<em>c</em> = -0.01) and so-call “direct effect” (<em>c’</em> = -0.03) of SES on delinquency. However, SES is negatively associated with both mediators, and each mediator has a comparably sized yet opposite effect on delinquency. The text results also indicate that the total indirect effect of SES on delinquency through both mediators is nearly zero as well (Mean bootstrapped indirect effect [<em>ab</em>] of SES on Delinquency through Strain and Risk = 0.02; standard error = 0.03; 95% CI = [-0.04, 0.08]). This should be unsurprising since we simulated the data so that the two indirect effects would equally offset one other, resulting in a total indirect effect of zero.</p>
<p>We could re-estimate the model, specifying each mechanism separately as a posited mediator, to calculate an estimate of the specific indirect effect through each mediator. Or, we could multiply the SES-&gt;Mediator path coefficient and the Mediator-&gt;Delinquency path coefficient together to get basic estimates of these specific indirect effects. For instance, using this “product of <em>ab</em> coefficients” approach, we would estimate a negative indirect effect of SES on delinquency through financial strain (-0.48 * 0.39) approximately equal to -0.19 and a positive indirect effect through perceived risk (-0.47 * -0.44) approximately equal to 0.21.<sup>5</sup> As expected, these countervailing indirect effects nearly perfectly offset one another!</p>
<p>So, this was a long-winded illustration of just one way that two variables might be <strong>causally related even in the absence of observing a (bivariate; total; direct) correlation</strong> between them!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="sec-caution" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-caution">Concluding cautions</h2>
<p>Finally, remember that although this example was inspired by a published study, ours is also a contrived example using simulated data designed to help you think more deeply about causation and (non)correlation. With simulated data, we create the rules and can ensure strong mediation assumptions are met. Yet, in the real world of messy observational data, there are often countless plausible causal models that could have generated the patterns of correlations in one’s data. For an excellent example, check out Julia Rohrer’s blog entry about <a href="https://www.the100.ci/2019/10/03/indirect-effect-ex-machina/">hunting for indirect effects</a> in the absence of a total effect (e.g., correlation) between X &amp; Y. She warns:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Third, be wary of mediation in the absence of a total effect. There may be scenarios in which it makes sense, but confounding may be the more plausible alternative explanation in other scenarios.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Her example beautifully, or frighteningly, illustrates how a collider can produce an erroneous inference about an indirect effect. You might be wondering to yourself: <em>what the heck is a collider</em>? Great question. To us, it is the scary monster in our statistical modeling closet that keeps us up at night; neither of us have ever really seen the monster, but we’ve read enough stories about it to be convinced that it is there. We’ll try tackling that one another time…</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Yes, I realize that I simulated the outcome variable, <em>Delinquency</em>, from a Poisson distribution - you got me. I should be specifying a generalized linear regression model (e.g., Poisson distribution with a log link) instead to avoid generating biasing estimates and accurately recover simulated parameters. But, then I would need to get into more <a href="https://ftp.cs.ucla.edu/pub/stat_ser/r363.pdf">advanced issues related to estimating indirect effects in nonlinear models</a>, which would distract from the key point here. Let’s get this straight: I adopted a simple modeling approach that is a poor match to the more complex (simulated) data I am analyzing for the sake of easing interpretation for the reader. Sound familiar? Now, it seems I have painted myself into a corner. Don’t worry - I have a mantra to get us out of this mess, courtesy of my dad: Do as I say and not as I do! If you are considering estimating indirect effects with real-world data, please check out <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4287269/">counterfactual causal mediation</a> approaches; various packages in R, like <a href="https://bs1125.github.io/CMAverse/">CMAverse</a> or <a href="https://bs1125.github.io/CMAverse/">medflex</a>, might do the trick. Moreover, in the course of conducting <em>real</em> science, don’t paint yourself into a corner. You’ll just be stuck in place for a long time and the job won’t be finished, or you’ll get paint on your shoes and make a huge mess that someone has to clean up.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>We used <code>geom_jitter()</code> to slightly offset or spread out observations that fall at the exact same place on the plot, which can be helpful in a scatterplot displaying a limited (e.g., ordinal) variable. With this method, observations cluster around their actual values rather than directly on the same crowded points, which permits you to see where data are plentiful or sparse along the observed distributions.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>It remains common for researchers to use the <a href="https://web.pdx.edu/~newsomj/semclass/ho_mediation.pdf">Sobel product of coefficients approach</a> for mediation tests and to estimate <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.810258/full">bias corrected bootstrapped confidence intervals</a>. However, for most observational data applications, I typically recommend using a <a href="https://www.publichealth.columbia.edu/research/population-health-methods/causal-mediation">causal mediation approach</a> that relies on counterfactual reasoning using a potential outcomes framework to estimate controlled and natural direct and indirect effects, along with <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/25152459221095827">careful consideration</a> and <a href="https://bmcresnotes.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13104-016-2163-7">transparent reporting</a> of the <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032315-021402#_i12">strong assumptions</a> required to interpret mediation results as causal effects.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>This is a very <a href="https://r-workshop.mindsci.net/mediation">basic mediation function</a> that applies the Sobel product of <em>ab</em> coefficients approach mentioned earlier. Remember, do as I say and not as I do! As noted above, I would not recommend this approach for most applications to observational data. However, in this case, the data were simulated from random distributions and a simple causal mediation structure without confounding or exposure-mediator interactions, so we know the <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032315-021402#_i12">strong causal mediation assumptions</a> hold. As such, this simple approach is sufficient for our purposes. That is, assuming you did us a solid by ignoring our Poisson-distributed outcome variable - and all the paint on our shoes.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Using the population parameters we specified to generate our simulated sample, the population <em>ab</em> indirect effect magnitudes equal (-0.5 * 0.5) = -0.25 and (-0.5 * -0.5) = 0.25, respectively.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{brauer2023,
  author = {Jon Brauer},
  title = {Causation Without {Correlation?}},
  date = {2023-04-10},
  url = {https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/causation-no-corr.html},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-brauer2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jon Brauer. 2023. <span>“Causation Without Correlation?”</span> April
10, 2023. <a href="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/causation-no-corr.html">https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/causation-no-corr.html</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>general</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>causality</category>
  <guid>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/causation-no-corr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[4]/empty-egg-dag3.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="135" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dr. Charles R. Tittle’s intellectual contributions</title>
  <dc:creator>Jon Brauer, with Katya Botchkovar and Carter Hay</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[3]/charles-memorial.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[3]/charles_smiling.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Dr.&nbsp;Charles R. Tittle</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The comments below were delivered in one of two <a href="https://tinyurl.com/yf3uexwu">tribute panels</a> dedicated to Dr.&nbsp;Charles R. Tittle’s intellectual and interpersonal contributions to criminology at the <a href="https://asc41.com/events/2021-asc-annual-meeting/">2021 American Society of Criminology annual meeting</a> in Chicago. While others contributed additional comments on the spot, the following include only those formally scheduled comments delivered about Charles’ intellectual contributions to the field. Click on a panel topic below to expand and view its contents:</p>
<p><strong>Charles R. Tittle Tribute I: Intellectual Contributions to Criminology</strong></p>
<details>
<summary>
Contributions to International Criminology (Katya Botchkovar)
</summary>
<section id="sec-charles_international" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-charles_international">Contributions to International Criminology</h2>
<p><strong>by <a href="https://cssh.northeastern.edu/faculty/ekaterina-botchkovar/">Katya Botchkovar</a></strong></p>
<p><em>Katya gave us permission to share the recorded video of her presentation, which was delivered remotely for the ASC tribute session:</em></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PgUFS5-Cum4" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section></details>
<details>
<summary>
Contributions to Measurement and Theory Testing (Carter Hay)
</summary>

<section id="sec-charles_measurement" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-charles_measurement">Contributions to Measurement and Theory Testing</h2>
<p><strong>by <a href="https://criminology.fsu.edu/faculty-and-staff/carter-hay">Carter Hay</a></strong></p>
<section id="introduction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p><em>Carter gave us permission to share the written notes for his comments delivered for the ASC tribute session:</em></p>
<p>Thank you Jon, and thank you for all of your organizing these sessions that allow us to reflect on Charles as such an important scholar and person for the field of criminology but also in our lives. My areas to cover are measurement and theory testing, and it was a wonderful idea to put those two together because when we look at Charles’s research in broad strokes, those two are inherently linked. I think of it in this way:</p>
<ul>
<li>Charles was as theoretical as they come — he approached each issue with a deep concern for theory.</li>
<li>But he also was immensely empirical; analyzing data and testing hypotheses are the core of his research activities.</li>
<li>But a third thing: He commonly used data that he had some part in collecting, which meant that he wasn’t having to rely on the measures available in secondary data; instead, he played a role in shaping new novel measures of theoretical concepts.</li>
</ul>
<p>This ultimately translated into extraordinary number of novel creative tests—studies that are among the best and most influential tests of a given theory, and this often was due in part to measurement.</p>
<p>And he did this for MANY different theories — by my count, it’s at 10 different theories not just that Charles was able to test, but that he was able to test with original data that enabled he and his co-authors to design their own measures:</p>
<ul>
<li>Differential association theory</li>
<li>Self-control theory</li>
<li>Deterrence theory</li>
<li>Reintegrative shaming and labeling theory</li>
<li>Strain theory, including general strain theory</li>
<li>Situational action theory</li>
<li>Colvin’s social support/coercion theory</li>
</ul>
<p>And then there also are theoretical topics that cut across <strong>multiple</strong> theories, including innovative work on:</p>
<ul>
<li>criminal motivations</li>
<li>morality and crime and religiosity and crime.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s not possible talk about all of those areas where Charles had a big impact with respect to measurement and empirical testing. I’m instead going to discuss two of those areas—deterrence and self-control—in some detail as illustrations of his general approach and his lasting influence.</p>
</section>
<section id="deterrence" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deterrence">Deterrence</h3>
<p>So the first area I want to focus on is deterrence. Charles’s work in this area most clearly begins with the Tittle (1969) article that used official data for the 50 states to reveal that the certainty of punishment—as indicated by the probability of imprisonment—was associated with lower crime and that severity (the length of prison sentences) also could reduce crime when certainty was at high levels. Charles’s key point in that article and in several others that followed in the 1970s was that deterrence needed to be taken seriously; it had been dismissed, but this wasn’t because good testing or good data had found problems; instead, he saw biases in play along with a tendency to go along with the conventional wisdom even when it wasn’t on firm ground.</p>
<p>Charles wasn’t in favor of deterrence theory, he wasn’t opposed to it—he wanted to test it effectively.</p>
<p>And his ideas on how best to test deterrence evolved fairly quickly and they would help shape the field. In 1972, Charles gets an NSF grant of $100,000 to fund a survey approach to testing deterrence theory. The results of that work were published in the book Sanctions and Social Deviance was published in 1980 and in some other articles published around that time.</p>
<p>Early in the book, he makes the case for studying deterrence with surveys, which of course, was quite different than his 1969 test that attracted so much attention—he expressed some real doubts that the macro-level research could ever explicitly reveal fear of sanctions as the operative mechanism, and this was crucial for distinguishing deterrence from other mechanisms by which punishment can affect crime.</p>
<p>Also, Charles felt that causal order issues would be tough to parse out because of how legal systems are embedded in complicated social contexts where history looms large. Even with sophisticated analyses, it was difficult to determine whether low certainty was leading to high crime, or conversely, whether high crime was leading to low certainty.</p>
<p>So he set out to try to address these two issues with a survey of roughly 2,000 adults randomly selected from three states: Iowa, Oregon, and New Jersey.</p>
<p>So on that first issue, Charles’s created an comprehensive measure of fear of sanctions. He identified multiple indicators of fear that were used for a multitude of different rule violations, with these capturing:</p>
<ul>
<li>the chances that people would find out?</li>
<li>would those be people you know?</li>
<li>would lots of people in the community find out?</li>
<li>would there be a loss of respect?</li>
<li>would it produce an arrest?</li>
<li>would produce jail?</li>
</ul>
<p>And then scores were further adjusted based on the person’s peer deviance—if most of the people that someone knew engaged in deviance, then them finding out probably shouldn’t be seen as increasing sanction fear.</p>
<p>Now, I’ll emphasize that Charles was not the only one pursuing this survey approach at this time (Waldo, Chiricos, Anderson), but his comprehensive approach to measurement was unique and his attention to scaling was meticulous.</p>
<ul>
<li>And let me mention something in connection to that — when you go to Charles’s CV, you see that 4 of his first 6 publications were explicitly measurement-oriented methodological pieces — measurement and scaling were the explicit priorities of the paper. This included articles or research notes from 1966-68 in American Journal of Sociology, Public Opinion Quarterly, Sociometry, and Social Forces. Collectively, they were cited more than 600 times and often re-printed.</li>
<li>These articles precede the articles in criminology that we think of regarding Charles’s career, and they dealt with things like political activity and bureaucratization, but there’s some foreshadowing that innovation and rigor in the area of measurement would be central to his work.</li>
</ul>
<p>But the scope of his survey-based approach to deterrence theory also was unique—it was a big project drawing a very diverse set of subjects from 3 states to ensure big variations in social contexts—which is critical to testing deterrence theory—a convenience sample taken from a group of people in the same social context simply isn’t the best test.</p>
<p>So that’s innovation #1 — taking the most rigorous approach possible to get at that mechanism of fear.</p>
<p>The second innovation dealt with this causal order issue, which had its own problems when using the survey approach. In cross-sectional studies, perceived certainty, severity, or fear of sanctions is measured at the time of the survey and offending is measured for the prior 6 or 12 months creating an obvious causal order concern in which offending precede perceptions of sanctions.</p>
<p>Now longitudinal panel data could be used but that’s difficult to come by and it creates the problem of lags—current perceptions are being used to predict future behavior, but what if perceptions of sanctions change and those current perceptions being measured at the time of the survey become outdated.</p>
<p>So Charles had an interesting fix for this — he measured projected deviance.</p>
<p>He asked this question: “If you were in a situation tomorrow where you had an extremely strong desire or need to [fill in the blank on the behavior], what are the chances that you would actually do it?”</p>
<p>So he used current perceptions of punishment to predict this measure of <strong>projected deviance</strong>, but he also measured prior deviance — it could be used as a conditioning variable or a control variable, and this measurement advance created much stronger causal inferences, especially in light of the later research that would show that projections of future deviance often were strongly correlated with actual deviance.</p>
<p>And this approach becomes the basis for many criminological studies that in some way make use of projected deviance or crime, intentions to offend, willingness to offend, and the vignette studies. These studies go beyond deterrence theory—studies on strain theory, differential association theory, self-control theory, and so on. In many instances, they cite Tittle’s earlier work—that’s especially true for the people in this room because there are a lot of us who have used these measures—but even when Tittle wasn’t cited, they typically lean on the same basic rational that Charles drew attention to more than 40 years ago:</p>
<p>the desire to use cross-sectional data to examine contemporaneous or short-term effects (rather than lagged effects) and to do so with stronger causal inferences.</p>
<p>Taking these two innovations together, what did Charles find? Findings that are very close to the current state of knowledge today. He found that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sanction fear reduces offending but fairly modestly.</li>
<li>Perceived informal sanctions tends to matter more than perceived formal sanctions.</li>
<li>And sanction fear generally has smaller effects than other theoretical variables, including moral commitments, social bonding, and differential associations.</li>
</ul>
<p>And Charles discovered lots of contingencies. His findings on this are immensely valuable; they laid the groundwork for interesting work to come on the idea of differential deterrability — with sanction fear operating more for some people and under some circumstances than others.</p>
<section id="sec-charles_deterrence" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-charles_deterrence">(Mark Stafford on deterrence)</h4>
<p>And this issue of contingencies is something that <a href="https://faculty.txst.edu/profile/1921048">Mark Stafford</a> emphasized in comments that he sent me. Mark had a family issue arise and he wasn’t able to travel to Chicago, but I wanted to share with you his comments on this issue:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Most deterrence researchers have paid lip-service to the idea that the threat of legal punishment probably interacts with other variables to affect the likelihood of crime. However, few have followed through on it, and no one as much as Charles. This was a central theme in his Sanctions and Social Deviance: The Question of Deterrence. A brief perusal of his deterrence studies over the years reveals that he looked at interactions between punishment threats and age, gender, informal punishments, self-control, and morality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Probably my favorite deterrence research by Charles focused on the possible interaction between punishment threats and motivation to commit crime. When I was a graduate student at the University of Arizona, I remember students (Mark Warr, Kirk Williams, Joe Rankin, and I) drinking with faculty (Jack Gibbs, Maynard Erickson, and Gary Jensen) on many occasions and discussing the obvious that punishment threats could not deter unless people were motivated to commit crime. We concluded, however, that motivation was too complex to capture in a simple measure. Move ahead decades later and that is exactly what Charles did – he measured motivation, and by simply asking people how much they wanted to commit crime. It turned out that this measure interacted with punishment threats to form a strong predictor of crime. Charles had a real talent of taking complex ideas and reducing them to their basics. What was too complex for the rest of us was easy for Charles. As a consequence, deterrence research is decades ahead of where it would have been without Charles. Perhaps it is hyperbole to compare Charles with Bentham and Beccaria, but I bet they would have liked to pick Charles’ brain about deterrence, and I bet Charles would tell them many things they got wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
</section>
<section id="self-control-theorymany-innovations-here" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="self-control-theorymany-innovations-here">Self-control theory—many innovations here</h3>
<p>Let me pivot now to self-control theory, which is an area where Charles’s contributions are immense. Many of the things we know about this theory are things we learned from Charles’s work.</p>
<p>If you look at Charles’s book reviews and commentaries on Gottfredson and Hirschi’s self-control theory, along with comments he’d make, three things were clear: (1) he saw some shortcomings in the theory, (2) he was nevertheless impressed by the case they made for self-control being an important neglected variable, and (3) he knew the theory would attract a lot of attention and testing.</p>
<p>And a question has occurred to me, one that I wished I’d asked him: In 1991, when Charles published one of the first reviews of Gottfredson and Hirschi’s book, did he anticipate that he himself would become so central to the empirical testing of the theory? I don’t know; maybe some of you do.</p>
<p>But his centrality is unquestioned.</p>
<p>It begins obviously with the Grasmick et al.&nbsp;self-control scale, which of course never gets referred to by the more long-winded label of the Grasmick, Tittle, Bursik, and Arneklev scale. But I do know that Charles was quite involved in the development of that scale because he once described the painstaking process he went through to try to identify items from the California Psychological Inventory, along with the recognition at various points that newly invented items also would be needed.</p>
<p>That resulting scale they came up with was examined with new data from the Oklahoma City Survey in one the first tests of the theory, and that scale or subsets of it of it have been used in scores of studies. And their original study also has been cited more than 2600 times. The bottom line is that this scale is in many ways the gold standard for measuring self-control in criminology, and the meticulous attention to its scaling has inspired further research into not just this measure but possible limitations in Gottfredson and Hirschi’s initial conceptualization of self-control.</p>
<p>Another notable innovation of Charles’s in this area involves the distinction between <strong>self-control ability and self-control interest</strong>, along with his creative attempts to empirically distinguish them. This 2004 article with Grasmick and Ward really displays Charles’s skill in getting at the interplay between theoretical creativity and measurement. This study went beyond the arguments of the theory to consider something new, but rather than just making an interesting argument, he used data and creative measurement to test it.</p>
<p>The argument was this: self-control theory and research had been really centered on the idea that people differ in the <strong>ABILITY (or capacity)</strong> to exercise self-control—some people have that ability, some people don’t. Charles’s point was that there also could be variation in self-control <strong>INTEREST</strong>. Here’s what he said:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>some people may have a strong capacity for self-control but may not always want to exercise it, while others may have weak self-control ability but have such a keen interest in controlling their deviant impulses that they end up conforming.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So these two things—ability and interest—can both be consequential and maybe they even interact with each other. Maybe the effect that one has on crime depends on how much of the other they possess.</p>
<ul>
<li>And he also raises this interesting possibility: self-control <strong>interest</strong> could be distinct from ability in being especially responsive to social stimuli. Maybe self-control ability is pretty stable in the way that the theory predicts, but interest—do you feel like exercising the self-control you really do possess or do you not feel like it?—is probably a much more situationally-fluid variable.</li>
</ul>
<p>So in this study, using Oklahoma City Survey data, they construct a measure of self-control interest, and they do so with items that place a person in a situation in which they have the option of REFRAINING from some deviant action, and they ask might come from refraining—</p>
<ul>
<li>would it allow them to feel proud?</li>
<li>to earn praise from others?</li>
<li>to avoid losing the respect of people they care about?</li>
<li>to avoid feeling guilty?</li>
</ul>
<p>If they say yes to these things, that’s an <strong>interest</strong> in exercising self-control.</p>
<p>And very quickly on the findings:</p>
<ul>
<li>They found that items measuring self-control interest coalesced nicely, loading on the same factor and not loading on a 2nd factor that including the traditional self-control ABILITY items.</li>
<li>Self control interest and self-control ability BOTH affected offending, often similarly, but when differences did emerge, it was <strong>INTEREST</strong> having the greater effect</li>
<li>There was some evidence of interaction such that self-control ability mattered less when a person was really INTERESTED in exercising self-control.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now there are other innovations that Charles had on self-control research, including measurement, but I’m running out of time. And there are other areas beyond deterrence and self-control theory that I would have liked to discuss. In particular, Charles’s research with Jon Brauer on Colvin’s social support and coercion theory in my mind provides a similar gold standard for testing that theory and measuring its concepts in both global and domain-specific ways.</p>
<p>But there’s not time, so I’ll just conclude by saying that the lasting influence of Charles’s research on theory testing and measurement comes back to a simple premise that seemed to always guide him, and we should be inspired to have it guide us as well. I believe that premise that really guided Charles was this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before reaching a conclusion on something, get the highest quality evidence you can, even if doing that is really hard. And it probably will be really hard. Press on and do it anyway.</li>
</ul>
</section></section></details>
<details>
<summary>
Advocate for Theoretical Science in Criminology (Jon Brauer)
</summary>


<section id="sec-charles_science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-charles_science">Advocate for Theoretical Science in Criminology</h2>
<p><strong>by <a href="https://jonbrauer.com">Jon Brauer</a></strong></p>
<section id="introduction-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-1">Introduction</h3>
<p>As my colleagues have described, Charles’ scholarship advanced so many areas of criminological inquiry, including: (1) several important substantive debates in criminology; (2) concept measurement &amp; theory testing using survey research; (3) and assessment of the generality of criminological patterns &amp; theories across international contexts. As scholars, many of us would love to make meaningful contributions to any single issue within one of these broad areas. The breadth, magnitude, and consistency of his contributions cements Charles Tittle’s status as one of the brightest stars in our criminological universe.</p>
<p>Throughout all this work, one would be hard-pressed to find a theory of crime or deviance that was popular or that emerged during his illustrious 55+ year career that Charles had not read, reviewed, and even directly tested himself. Think about that a moment. He did not devote his time to becoming a specialist in any one theory or any particular area of inquiry. Rather, he devoted his time to becoming a specialist in countless theories and interdisciplinary areas relevant to his vast domain of inquiry – human behavior. That is, Charles embodied a generalist or Renaissance model of scholarship that seems all too rare in today’s knowledge silos, perpetuated by narrow training specializations, focused research funding and accomplishments, and exponential growth in short, quick-hitting publications.</p>
<p>Charles’ varied contributions stemmed directly from his philosophy of science. He was not simply jumping from latest fad to latest fad. He was not an opportunist doggedly seeking to aim his crosshairs at every emergent idea from other hard-working scholars. He was not just publishing because that is what we do. No, Charles had much loftier aims with his research and writing. Individually and in their totality, his publications reflect his deep commitment to the health and vibrancy of the field of criminology. In fact, to Charles, the health and vibrancy of a scientific field is tantamount to the health and vibrancy of <em>theoretical development</em> in that field.</p>
<p>Likewise, Charles devoted his entire career – and such a massive portion of his precious hours spent on this Earth – to trying to improve our theories: by reading them, thinking about them, testing them, critiquing them, developing them, and by advocating for and training others to do the same.</p>
</section>
<section id="charles-philosophy-the-mansion-of-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="charles-philosophy-the-mansion-of-science">Charles’ Philosophy &amp; The Mansion of Science</h3>
<p>Charles was not known as someone who spent much time writing explicitly about philosophy of science. Yet, he certainly had a coherent working scientific philosophy – his belief in and advocacy for the centrality of theories to scientific progress was a cornerstone – and while his scientific philosophy was readily apparent to those who knew him well, it also emanated from his teachings and writings.</p>
<p>In the introductory lecture to one of his foundational graduate theory courses, Charles would begin by describing the “mansion of science” as having many rooms, with these rooms divided into blocks representing different paradigms or models of science. After describing other complementary or competing models of science, such as descriptive, <em>vehrstehen</em>, engineering, critical, nihilistic approaches, and the like, Charles would then endorse the “theoretical science” model, which he viewed as the most efficient, reliable means of fostering scientific progress. He would also pointedly profess that the theoretical science model occupied the most rooms and held the best real estate in the mansion of science.</p>
<p>In this regard, Charles views were heavily influenced by works such as Richard Braithwaite’s classic 1953 book, <em>Scientific Explanation</em>, and by Paul Reynolds’ 1971 book, <em>A Primer in Theory Construction</em>. Reynolds’ book was particularly influential to Charles’ working scientific philosophy.</p>
<p>Like Reynolds, Charles viewed the goals of science and scientific activity as:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>providing <em>typologies</em>, or identification and organization of phenomena into conceptual categories of similar and different things;</li>
<li>permitting the accurate <em>prediction</em> of future phenomena;</li>
<li>providing accurate <em>explanations</em> for past phenomena; and</li>
<li>providing people a <em>sense of understanding</em> about how and why phenomena occur via full articulation of the causal mechanisms linking changes in some concepts (causes) with changes in other concepts (effects).</li>
</ol>
<p>(Many would add the <em>potential for control</em> of phenomena as a secondary consequence of accurate explanation and prediction, though Charles was infamously resistant to making the jump from <em>is</em>-based knowledge to <em>ought</em>-based control or policy prescriptions given the state of our evidence, to which I will return soon.)</p>
<p>If these indeed are the primary goals of scientific activity, then theory development is central to science. Theories provide our typologies, or our conceptual categories and shared language about phenomena. Theories are our explanations of phenomena, and we use them to generate and test predictions. Likewise, theories are our (variably) formalized answers to why and how things occur and, as such, they do, or they fail to, provide us with a sense of understanding about – or potential for effective control of – phenomena. So, for Charles, science goes as our theories go. Also, like Reynolds, Charles viewed scientific progress or the successful pursuit of these goals as occurring most efficiently through what is reminiscent of a Lakatosian process involving:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Observing, describing, &amp; making initial empirical generalizations about phenomena -&gt;</li>
<li>Developing initial hypotheses, or what Charles endearingly called “simple theories,” that explain some of those descriptive patterns or empirical generalizations -&gt;</li>
<li>Rigorous testing of these (often numerous, varied, &amp; competing) hypotheses or “simple theories” -&gt;</li>
<li>Slow accumulation of knowledge from these tests; identification of additional generalizations &amp; negative cases; and, ultimately, the development of new theories that better account for patterns observed in accumulated knowledge base through processes such as theoretical invention, elaboration, or integration.</li>
</ol>
<p>Charles most explicitly outlines his adherence to this philosophy in one of my favorite pieces of his – a chapter in Gilbert Geis &amp; Mary Dodge’s wonderful 2002 book, <em>Lessons of Criminology</em> (see p.32-3), entitled “Confessions of a Reluctant but Committed Criminologist.” In it, he describes the eventual development of adequate theories ultimately is what will permit “explanation, prediction, and sometimes control of criminal/deviant or other human behavior.” He warns, a la Lakatos, that “[t]he whole process, however, is long and tedious, with knowledge growing in a cumulative process. One study means nothing; collections of large numbers and varieties of progressively more refined studies are required.” (p.33).</p>
</section>
<section id="lessons-of-a-reluctant-but-committed-criminologist" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lessons-of-a-reluctant-but-committed-criminologist">Lessons of a Reluctant but Committed Criminologist</h3>
<p>In that Reflections chapter, Charles also described the first four important lessons of his academic career, which crystallized during his time on the faculty at Washington State University. Those are that:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Our body of verified scientific knowledge is exceptionally weak</li>
<li>[Theoretical] Science is the best model for criminological work</li>
<li>Bias is pervasive in social science, including criminology, &amp; is an archenemy of knowledge</li>
<li>Recommendations or guidelines from criminologists for social policy should be delayed until there is a strong scientific base of relevant knowledge</li>
</ol>
<p>Charles then states: “…to fully comprehend their import [of these four lessons] one must share certain definitions and orientations about the meaning of science.” That is, one must share a view of science as ideally involving the slow process of knowledge construction through careful observation, empirical generalization, explanation, testing, evolution of community consensus about the adequacy an explanation following accumulation of supporting and challenging test results, development of refined explanations under more general explanatory schemes or adequate theories, and rinse and repeat.</p>
<p>Charles worked with intention according to these lessons. His strong dedication to theory development always involved frequent testing of others’ ideas; ultimately, these efforts also culminated in his magnum opus, <em>Control Balance: Toward a General Theory of Deviance</em>. His advocacy for theoretical science was readily apparent in his book, in his reactions to critics of the book, and in his later published refinements to control balance theory.</p>
</section>
<section id="culmination-in-his-magnum-opus-control-balance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="culmination-in-his-magnum-opus-control-balance">Culmination in His Magnum Opus, <em>Control Balance</em></h3>
<p>In the first sentence of his published reply in <em>Theoretical Criminology</em> to John Braithwaite’s review of <em>Control Balance</em>, Charles summarized the dual aims of his book:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“<em>Control Balance</em>… tries to do two things. One is to set forth a paradigm for theory building and the other is to present an exemplar to be used as a starting point for the application of that paradigm. An important theme contained within the paradigm is that theory must represent the collective efforts of the community of scholars. No specific theoretical effort should be owned by anybody, a specific formulation is always tentative, and theory cumulates and improves as many individuals add their ideas and the results of research to the enterprise…”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The paradigm he envisions here is a theoretical science of criminology oriented toward the collective, collaborative construction of causal process theories. The first half of <em>Control Balance</em> described this paradigm in detail. He started by illustrating both the utility and deficiencies inherent in existing “simple theories” of crime and deviance, thereby convincingly highlighting the need for a new paradigm such as his – and likely disaffecting at least as many readers as he convinced in the process. He then described core features of an adequate theory, calling for criminologists to work towards developing theories with sufficient <em>breadth</em>, <em>comprehensiveness</em>, <em>precision</em>, and <em>depth</em>. He subsequently argued that integration around central causal processes or mechanisms, as opposed to invention or elaboration, holds the greatest promise for collaborative efforts at effective theory development.</p>
<p>I am convinced our field would benefit from widely disseminating these initial chapters as a touchstone by which we judge our ideas and organize our efforts. In particular, I think we really need collective commitment to improving the <em>precision</em> of our causal predictions – to “identifying the conditions that influence exactly when and to what degree causal processes will unfold, the nature of the causal effects, the time interval between the proposed causes and expected effects” (or timing, magnitude, and functional form), and other contingencies that specify the scope or conditions under which the causal processes and predictions are expected to vary.</p>
<p>Additionally, Charles thought our best chance at accumulating a meaningful body of scientific knowledge in criminology was for us to build a community of like-minded scholars dedicated to the same cause. Toward this end, foreshadowing post-replication crisis movements, Charles put forth provocative suggestions for a more collaborative peer review system (in <em>The Criminologist</em>), and he advocated for changes to our incentive structures and training regimes to foster theoretical science pursuits. For instance, in his 2002 Reflections chapter, Charles stated (p.33):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“For science to operate and to produce the desired outcomes, it must be supported by a community of scholars dedicated to the scientific enterprise. This community of scholars must structure itself to reward those who follow its dictates and ignore those who do not, and it must socialize new members in the values and methods of science. Those values include dedication to: (1) knowledge gained through the scientific method, (2) objectivity, (3) the search for truth, (4) open discussion and sharing of information, and (5) skepticism and mutual criticism. Science, therefore, is not value free. It is absolutely committed to a value system – the values of science. Moreover, science is a jealous master, insisting that other values (ideology and personal commitments) be rejected or overcome, at least when attempting to do science.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Charles also insisted that, this being a difficult task, we scientists organize our community to check competing values by “insisting on review by demanding critics, rewarding those who work against their own personal interests and values, and granting prestige to those who most fully exhibit the ideals of science while stigmatizing those who betray the cause.” If we meet these ideals, Charles asserted that “science can lead to knowledge that is more reliable, satisfying, and useful than any other paradigm by which people seek to understand human behavior and social organization.” However, “practicing science is difficult, especially for those who study social phenomena.” So, “the best that we criminologists can do is to practice science to the fullest extent possible, recognizing that our work often falls short and being cautious in our claims.”</p>
</section>
<section id="back-to-the-mansion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="back-to-the-mansion">Back to the Mansion</h3>
<p>How did Charles think we criminologists are doing in this regard? Well, remember that mansion of science? I will refrain from elaborating on our self-derogatory conversations about which floors (or subfloors) our fields – sociology, criminology, &amp; criminal justice – took up in the mansion. What I will say, though, is that over their final several years attending ASC, Charles and his close friend Jim Short would frequently lament about the diminishing number of ASC panels devoted specifically to theory compared to the burgeoning number of panels representing work within those other paradigms. Moreover, in our last conversations, Charles expressed much pessimism about the health of criminology and the future of theoretical development in our field.</p>
<p>I certainly empathized with his viewpoint – much more so than I let him know in those conversations. However, I also pointed to various developments – such as emerging theoretical solutions to the replication crisis; advances in formal modeling; sophisticated theorizing and prediction in the Bayesian movement; and theoretical advancements tied to the counterfactual causal revolution – that I think hold much promise for interdisciplinary social science. He was also encouraged when I summarized Proctor &amp; Niemeyer’s new book, <em>Mechanistic Criminology</em>, which (I think) in many ways represents a new generation of criminologists carrying Charles’ paradigmatic torch into exciting unexplored theoretical territory and, likewise, holds much promise for our field.</p>
<p>Most importantly, across more than a half-century of scholarship, Charles practiced science to the fullest extent possible, he never failed to recognize that his work often fell short, and likewise he was consistently cautious in his claims. In doing so, he was perhaps most effective as a relentless advocate for theoretical science in criminology in leading us by example. His writings will live on in the scholarly record – with each of his individual studies meaning nothing on their own but, collectively, each contributing as “grist for the mill” of science in the long and tedious process of cumulative knowledge production. Additionally, likely without explicitly intending to do so, he built a community of like-minded scholars – including many of you in this room – who share his pursuit and, in doing so, make his journey and his immense sacrifices on the alter of science meaningful.</p>
</section>
<section id="community-building-by-example" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-building-by-example">Community Building by Example</h3>
<p>Finally, as a last testament to his advocacy and community building by example, I would like to close with quotes from a few students of Charles’ students – these are young scholars, a generation removed, most of whom never had the pleasure of meeting the man, the myth, the legend in black jeans and cowboy boots.</p>
<p>As these excerpts come from a list of longer quotes that I collected for a different purpose – to read to Charles as he neared the end – I have kept the authors’ names anonymous here. They are a small sample, but I think these effectively represent the legacy of influence that Charles Tittle has left with his students and colleagues.</p>
<p>First, two assistant professors who never met Charles but had read Control Balance in a graduate course state that reading Control Balance theory reminded them:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“of the creativity, effort, and time it takes to actually put forth a theory. Your review of previous criminological theories and their weaknesses to even set up Control Balance Theory shows how meticulous you were in theory building approach. In today’s race to publish, it is easy to lose sight of the difficulty and time it takes to develop a comprehensive framework for thinking about crime.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An advanced doctoral student states that “Dr.&nbsp;Charles Tittle was the first scholar who was able to convince me of the value and power of theory and” that reading <em>Control Balance</em> “was, in the deepest sense of the word, enlightening.” After reading it, this student says:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I now think theory development and testing are some of the most important scientific endeavors social scientists can and should engage in–moreover, I find them the most intellectually satisfying! It turns out I love theory. His book, his articles, and even discussions with his former students influenced by his work have certainly shaped my trajectory as a student and a scholar. And I am certain that echoes of his influence will continue to shape the rest of my academic career.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An advanced graduate student states that:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Control Balance had a tremendous influence on me… in illustrating and breaking down all the complexities that go into theory building and integration. We all know human behavior is a complicated phenomenon, but the way Control Balance looks at the integration of theories to build a general theory of crime and how it connects the numerous converging variables, which each exists on their own continuum, is just artistry. Dr.&nbsp;Tittle’s work really stuck with me in enumerating how much work we have ahead of us in our field (and in many other fields) to truly understanding the nature of crime and deviance. His call for the continued elaboration on his work really sets a precedence for how we as scholars should approach and encourage critiques, elaboration, and hopefully integration on our own work instead of falling into the time-old tradition of pure competition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A newer doctoral student says that prior to reading <em>Control Balance</em> for a course:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I had not, in fact, taken any interest in theory construction or debate, believing it to be outside of my level of comprehension. Upon reading Control Balance, I realized that theory is not a tool that one can afford to overlook out of fear of dissonance and ambiguity. As an individual who has only just begun to break into the world of theoretical science…, your book could not have come to me at a better time. For that, I thank you and proudly take up your call toward better theory, debate, and collaboration…”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, an advanced doctoral student explains various lessons learned from Charles work:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“…your [Reflections chapter] taught me that it is important to be nice in the work that we do (from your conversation with Dr.&nbsp;Short), that it is okay to do science for the sake of science, and not to be supremely concerned with policy relevance. Along similar lines, your article The Arrogance of Public Sociology taught me to employ healthy skepticism regarding research that is primarily public/policy driven. Additionally, your work on Control Balance Theory has helped me see where existing theories are deficient, how they can potentially be improved, and how complex it is to formulate a grand theory of deviant/criminal behavior.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This student also reflected on how Charles’ legacy of mentorship was indirectly influential in teaching the importance of:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“…increasing methodological rigor in research methodology/statistical analysis, creating a more transparent and cumulative science, being honest about things we do not know in the field, and an appreciation for the importance of testing and refining criminological theory. … I am forever grateful to you and cannot wait to pass on these principles to students of my own one day.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I could not have said that better myself. Thank you, Charles.</p>
</section></section></details>
<p>For additional reflections about Charles from a few of his former students and colleagues, see Washington State University’s wonderful <a href="https://soc.wsu.edu/socnews/remembering-charles-tittle-1938-2021/"><em>Remembering Charles Tittle</em></a> memorial tribute.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{brauer,withkatyabotchkovarandcarterhay2023,
  author = {Jon Brauer, with Katya Botchkovar and Carter Hay},
  title = {Dr. {Charles} {R.} {Tittle’s} Intellectual Contributions},
  date = {2023-03-12},
  url = {https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/charles-memorial.html},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-brauer,withkatyabotchkovarandcarterhay2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jon Brauer, with Katya Botchkovar and Carter Hay. 2023. <span>“Dr.
Charles R. Tittle’s Intellectual Contributions.”</span> March 12, 2023.
<a href="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/charles-memorial.html">https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/charles-memorial.html</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>general</category>
  <guid>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[3]/charles-memorial.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[3]/charles_smiling.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Check out some of our favorite sites</title>
  <dc:creator>Jon Brauer and Jake Day</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[2]/favorite_links.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[2]/DALL-E-melting_heart_of_statistics_in_Dali_style_80.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Melting heart of statistics in Salvadore Dali’s surrealist style, by DALL-E</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We have learned so much from blogs, bookdowns, and videos openly shared by others. Here, we compiled a list of some of our favorite resources.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>This list is far from exhaustive; there are too many influential sources to recall and credit as deserved. Nonetheless, we felt it would be helpful to pull together some of those that we routinely find ourselves revisiting and recommending to others.</p>
<section id="statistics-especially-bayesian-approaches-and-more" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="statistics-especially-bayesian-approaches-and-more">statistics, especially Bayesian approaches, and more</h2>
<p><strong>Andrew Gelman’s</strong> <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/">blog</a> is perhaps our favorite place to go for musings on all things statistics, especially <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2022/08/10/bayesian-inference-continues-to-completely-solve-the-multiple-comparisons-problem/">Bayesian inference</a>, <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2022/12/02/not-frequentist-enough-2/">frequentist evaluation</a>, <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2021/03/11/regression-discontinuity-analysis-is-often-a-disaster-so-what-should-you-do-instead-do-we-just-give-up-on-the-whole-natural-experiment-idea-heres-my-recommendation/">causal inference</a>, <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2023/03/09/the-butterfly-and-the-piranha-understanding-the-generalizability-and-reproducibility-crisis-from-statistical-and-political-perspectives-my-talk-at-the-university-of-minnesota-political-science/">multilevel modeling</a>, <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2022/04/05/confidence-intervals-compatability-intervals-uncertainty-intervals/">uncertainty</a>, and <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2018/12/04/bayes-statistics-reproducibility-many-serious-problems-statistics-practice-arise-bayesian-inference-not-bayesian-enough-frequentist-evaluation-not-frequentist/">reproducibility</a>. We also appreciate the frequent attention paid to <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2019/09/11/exchange-with-deborah-mayo-on-abandoning-statistical-significance/">philosophy of science issues</a> throughout many posts. Bonus: if you browse long enough, you might even stumble upon an answer to the question that perennially motivates a career crisis for us: <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2021/03/12/the-social-sciences-are-useless-so-why-do-we-study-them-heres-a-good-reason/">The social sciences are useless, so why do we even study them?</a>.</p>
<p>Speaking of Andrew Gelman - do you want to <a href="https://avehtari.github.io/ROS-Examples/">learn regression</a> or <a href="http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/book/">Bayesian modeling</a>? Gelman and colleagues’ books and accompanying websites are excellent resources on these topics. However, our go-to resource for learning statistics from a Bayesian framework is <strong>Richard McElreath’s</strong> <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Statistical-Rethinking-A-Bayesian-Course-with-Examples-in-R-and-STAN/McElreath/p/book/9780367139919"><em>Rethinking Statistics (2nd Ed.)</em></a>. All code from the book and a corresponding R package (<code>rethinking</code>) are <a href="https://xcelab.net/rm/statistical-rethinking/">openly shared online</a>, and McElreath’s brilliant <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLDcUM9US4XdNUolPcpdclIg4Ijt4dqxVc">video lectures on YouTube</a>, which he routinely updates, simply are without equal. Seriously - stop reading our site now and go work your way through those lectures and associated code.</p>
<p>As much as we love McElreath’s book and lectures for learning a Bayesian approach to data analysis, we usually rely on <strong>Paul Bürkner’s</strong> “Bayesian regression models using Stan,” or <code>brms()</code>, <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/brms/">R package</a> for everyday Bayesian modeling tasks. In addition to the <code>brms()</code> package, we recommend checking out Bürkner’s <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/projects/">research projects</a> and <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/publications/">publications</a>. In particular, we especially appreciate his work on modeling and visualizing <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/projects/#mu-bmb">uncertainty in (Bayesian) model comparison</a> and his efforts to incorporate cumulative link functions for modeling <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/9qkhj/">monotonic effects of ordinal predictors in Bayesian regression models</a>. Meanwhile, we are particularly fond of Bürkner’s <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/brms/articles/index.html"><code>brms</code> vignettes</a>, especially those on <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/brms/articles/brms_multivariate.html">multivariate (i.e., multiple response variables) models</a> and <a href="https://paul-buerkner.github.io/brms/articles/brms_monotonic.html">monotonic effects</a>. You can also watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1qeXD4NQ4To">his talk on multilevel modeling in <code>brms</code></a> for free courtesy of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@generableHQ/about"><span class="citation" data-cites="GenerableHQ">@GenerableHQ</span></a>.</p>
<p>So, what if you want to learn Bayesian analysis from McElreath’s book and lectures, yet you also want to follow along with his examples using the <code>brms()</code> package? Enter <strong>Solomon Kurz</strong>, the data science hero we need but do not deserve. Kurz has dedicated an unfathomable amount of energy to developing Bayesian translations of some of our favorite statistics books into R language and the <code>brms()</code> package, then sharing these valiant efforts in <a href="https://solomonkurz.netlify.app/book/">open-access bookdown projects</a>. Specifically, here are Kurz’s translations of the <a href="https://bookdown.org/content/3890">first edition</a> and <a href="https://bookdown.org/content/4857">second edition</a> of McElreath’s book. Additionally, many years agom Jake and I initially learned longitudinal data analysis in the SAS program using <a href="https://academic.oup.com/book/41753">Singer and Willett’s (2003) now-classic book</a>; Kurz actually offers a free <a href="https://bookdown.org/content/4253/">tidyverse and brms translation</a> of their book as well! Likewise, he has similarly translated two other favorites of ours: <a href="https://bookdown.org/content/3686/">Kruschke’s <em>Doing Bayesian Data Analysis</em></a> and Hayes’ <a href="https://bookdown.org/content/b472c7b3-ede5-40f0-9677-75c3704c7e5c/"><em>Introduction to Mediation, Moderation, and Conditional Process Analysis</em></a>. If you make it through all that free content, then we suggest heading over to his informative <a href="https://solomonkurz.netlify.app/blog/">blog on data analysis in R</a> for more useful content.</p>
<p>There are so many others worth mentioning in this section but, in respect of your time, we will simply share the rest in list format:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Matthew Kay’s</strong> <a href="https://www.mjskay.com/">site</a> for inspiration on communicating and visualizing uncertainty with <code>tidybayes</code> and <code>ggdist</code>. In particular, we recommend Kay’s various package vignettes, such as this one on <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tidybayes/vignettes/tidybayes.html">using tidy data with Bayesian models</a> and this one on <a href="https://mjskay.github.io/ggdist/articles/slabinterval.html">slab + interval stats and geoms with ggdist</a>. Also, you can watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PqCaljvE89k">Kay’s talk on visualizing uncertainty</a> courtesy of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@generableHQ/about"><span class="citation" data-cites="GenerableHQ">@GenerableHQ</span></a>.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Andrew Heiss’s</strong> <a href="https://www.andrewheiss.com/blog/">blog</a>, especially entries on <a href="https://www.andrewheiss.com/blog/2022/09/26/guide-visualizing-types-posteriors/">different types of posterior predictions</a>, <a href="https://www.andrewheiss.com/blog/2022/05/20/marginalia/">marginal effects terminology</a>, and <a href="https://www.andrewheiss.com/blog/2022/11/29/conditional-marginal-marginaleffects/">conditional and marginal effects in multilevel models</a></li>
<li><strong>Aki Vehtari’s</strong> <a href="https://users.aalto.fi/~ave/">work</a>, especially that on <a href="https://avehtari.github.io/modelselection/">model selection</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1507.04544">model checking and cross-validation</a>, and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.12335">posterior stacking</a>. Also, be sure to check out his various <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCcFy4yl5IyWeqJ5z2g1U8yg">videos</a>, like this one on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lKRRyrPxxeU">Bayesian workflow</a> or his open access course videos on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLBqnAso5Dy7O0IVoVn2b-WtetXQk5CDk6">Bayesian data analysis</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Michael Betancourt’s</strong> <a href="https://betanalpha.github.io/writing/">writing</a> and <a href="https://betanalpha.github.io/speaking/">videos</a> on probabilistic modeling in Stan, and especially those on adopting a <a href="https://betanalpha.github.io/assets/case_studies/principled_bayesian_workflow.html">principled Bayesian workflow</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.the100.ci/"><strong>The 100% CI</strong></a> is a newer favorite. We are especially fond of Julia Rohrer’s (one of the site’s authors) various writing related to causal inference, like these on <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2515245917745629">directed acyclic graphs</a>, <a href="https://www.the100.ci/2017/03/14/that-one-weird-third-variable-problem-nobody-ever-mentions-conditioning-on-a-collider/">collider bias</a>, and what can go wrong with <a href="https://www.the100.ci/2023/03/07/non-representative-samples-what-could-possibly-go-wrong/">nonrepresentative samples</a>.</li>
<li>The <strong>Data Colada</strong> <a href="https://datacolada.org/">blog</a> offers great analysis on various topics. For instance, they write about <a href="https://datacolada.org/76">replication</a>, conduct <a href="https://datacolada.org/81">preregistered replications</a>, and even offer an R package (<a href="https://datacolada.org/100"><code>groundhog</code></a>) for improving reproducibililty of code. They also have interesting things to say about <a href="https://datacolada.org/104">meta-analysis</a> and problems with common techniques such as <a href="https://datacolada.org/58">funnel plots</a> and <a href="https://datacolada.org/30">trim and fill “corrections”</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Dan Quintana,</strong> co-host of the <a href="https://everythinghertz.com/"><em>Everything Hertz</em> podcast</a>, also has a <a href="https://www.dsquintana.blog/">blog</a> containing great resources for meta-analysis and more in R.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Daniel Lakens’</strong> blog, the <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/">20% statistician</a>, is rife with useful posts about two of our favorite topics - statistics and philosophy of science. Some of our favorites include posts about <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2021/11/why-p-values-should-be-interpreted-as-p.html"><em>p</em>-values</a>, <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2020/03/effect-sizes-and-power-for-interactions.html">power</a> and <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2014/12/observed-power-and-what-to-do-if-your.html">observed power</a>, the <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2017/05/how-power-analysis-implicitly-reveals.html">smallest effect size of interest</a>, or whether <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2019/01/does-your-philosophy-of-science-matter.html">philosophy of science matters in practice</a> (we think it does a lot in criminology). Several of his lecture videos are also available online, including <a href="https://youtu.be/gVqFAQC8O14">this one</a> that corresponds to another favorite post discussing why more of us should seriously consider <a href="https://daniellakens.blogspot.com/2019/11/do-you-really-want-to-test-hypothesis.html">whether we are really ready to test a hypothesis</a> in our research. Lakens has combined and expanded on a lot of these materials in his open access book, <a href="https://lakens.github.io/statistical_inferences/index.html"><em>Improving Your Statistical Inferences</em></a> and his free <a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/statistical-inferences">coursera course</a> of the same name.<br>
</li>
<li>Of all the podcasts we enjoy, the <strong>Quantitude</strong> <a href="https://quantitudepod.org/?s=bayes">podcast</a> deserves a special shout-out for its highly informative yet quirky and accessible introduction to all sorts of important issues in statistics. Now, if only the hosts would join the Bayesian <a href="https://quantitudepod.org/s2e04-bayesian-wake-up-call/">dark side</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Jacob Kaplan</strong> has <a href="https://jacobdkaplan.weebly.com/books.html">multiple resources</a> related to R that are geared specifically to Criminologists. Perhaps most notably is a free online book <a href="https://crimebythenumbers.com/"><em>Crime by the Numbers: A Criminologist’s Guide to R</em></a>. Kaplan has great programming skills and, as such, many of his examples rely on base R functionality more so than ours do.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="learning-data-science-with-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-data-science-with-r">learning data science with R</h2>
<p>While there is so much to learn from resources found at the links shared above, those are not the first places we send our students and friends that are interested in learning data science skills in R, yet that lack any R programming experience. We find the following links to be especially useful for these purposes - so much so that they deserve their own dedicated section! Of course, we also hope our <a href="../../course-materials">course materials</a> might be useful in this regard to some of you.</p>
<p><strong>Danielle Navarro’s</strong> <a href="https://blog.djnavarro.net/">blog</a> is as delightful as it is informative. The blog is a model for reproducible R programming and showcases Danielle’s inspiring art throughout the site (see more of Danielle’s <a href="https://art.djnavarro.net/">computational art here</a>). The newest version of the blog often focuses on technical posts addressing issues beyond our range of program expertise. However, we love various topical essays from earlier blog renditions, <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/wxn58/">like this one on preregistration</a>, and we strongly recommend Danielle’s <a href="https://robust-tools.djnavarro.net/">Data Science with R</a> course and associated video tutorials for R beginners or those interested in leveling up their R skills.</p>
<p><strong>Allison Hill’s</strong> <a href="https://www.apreshill.com/blog/">blog</a> is a great place to find resources for learning to do as well as to teach R-related topics. For instance, we especially appreciate her post on teaching <a href="https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2020-05-how-i-teach-r-markdown/">R Markdown</a>, which was influential in creating our own courses, as well as her post on transitioning to <a href="https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2022-04-we-dont-talk-about-quarto/">Quarto</a>, which was helpful to us in creating our blog.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://psyteachr.github.io/">psyTeachR</a> website is a phenomenal repository of resources for learning and teaching reproducible research using R. They offer a wealth of open access courses and tutorials for undergraduate and graduate levels.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://easystats.github.io/easystats/"><code>easystats</code></a> collection of R packages is a great place for those new to R to learn basic skills related to modeling, visualization, and reporting within a relatively unified framework. Those new Unlike curated nature of R and package conflicts Those transitioning from curated statistical packages to R’s open-source environment, with its <em>a la carte</em> format and associated challenges (e.g., package conflicts), may find the <code>easystats</code> suite of packages especially helpful.</p>
<p>Of course, we also love creating data visualizations with <code>ggplot2</code> in R, so we owe a huge shout out to <strong>Hadley Wickham</strong> for all his R programming efforts and clear tutorials and foundational texts, which you can learn more about and freely access via his <a href="https://hadley.nz/">website</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="creating-a-website" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="creating-a-website">creating a website</h2>
<p>If you want to learn to create your own website or blog using R, we recommend checking out Andrew Rapp’s <a href="https://albert-rapp.de/posts/13_quarto_blog_writing_guide/13_quarto_blog_writing_guide.html">ultimate guide to creating a Quarto blog</a>, Beatriz Mills’ guide to <a href="https://beamilz.com/posts/2022-06-05-creating-a-blog-with-quarto/en/">creating a blog with Quarto in 10 steps</a>, Samantha Csik’s tutorial on <a href="https://samanthacsik.github.io/posts/2022-10-24-quarto-blogs/">adding a blog to your existing Quarto website</a>, and Ezekiel Ekunola’s instructions for <a href="https://www.codementor.io/@ekunolaeasybuoy/setting-up-domain-with-namecheap-netlify-12yiksvig6">setting up a personalized domain address for your site</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to R-based visualizations, we relied heavily upon <strong>Allison Horst’s</strong> <a href="https://allisonhorst.com/allison-horst">website</a>, where she freely shares amazing data science, statistics, and R themed artwork, to help improve our site’s aesthetics. We also had fun generating custom images and art using the artificial intelligence system <a href="https://openai.com/product/dall-e-2">DALL-E</a>.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{brauerandjakeday2023,
  author = {Jon Brauer and Jake Day},
  title = {Check Out Some of Our Favorite Sites},
  date = {2023-03-11},
  url = {https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/favorite_links.html},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-brauerandjakeday2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jon Brauer and Jake Day. 2023. <span>“Check Out Some of Our Favorite
Sites.”</span> March 11, 2023. <a href="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/favorite_links.html">https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/favorite_links.html</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>general</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>causality</category>
  <category>bayesian</category>
  <guid>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[2]/favorite_links.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[2]/DALL-E-melting_heart_of_statistics_in_Dali_style_80.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome to the reluctant criminologists</title>
  <dc:creator>Jon Brauer and Jake Day</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[1]/welcome-blog.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[1]/RC_logo_white.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Reluctant criminologists logo</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="why-are-we-doing-this" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-are-we-doing-this">Why are we doing this?</h2>
<p>First, this site is intended primarily as a central repository for conveniently sharing our course material and preliminary ideas with students and colleagues. It allows us to simply point people to a website rather than sending large html files via email or proliferating dropbox links. If it serves only this purpose effectively, we will be happy.</p>
<p>Second, this site is a direct consequence of our recent efforts to re-tool our approaches to doing science. We think this site will serve as evidence for how much we have learned - and likely as even stronger evidence of how much more we have yet to learn.</p>
<p>Of course, this begs the question: Why have we been re-tooling our approaches to science? Well, answering that question requires a longer conversation with multiple threads, and we anticipate weaving some of those threads into our future blog posts. For now, it may be clear from our posted materials that we are motivated to act in response to increasing concerns about replication failures across multiple scientific disciplines and awareness of subsequent reforms. We are also motivated by the perception that our academic disciplines of sociology and criminology, with some exceptions, may be lagging behind other fields <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2016/09/22/why-is-the-scientific-replication-crisis-centered-on-psychology/">like psychology</a> in self-reflection on these important issues and widespread adoption of <a href="https://www.economicscience.org/downloads/ReplicationWhitePaper.pdf">potentially effective reforms</a>. Likewise, we are moved by our own experiences with reproducing <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0049124119826158">high-profile work</a> and attempting to raise awareness through the traditional academic peer-review publication process about concerns regarding underpowered null hypothesis significance tests and common misinterpretations of null findings from such tests.</p>
<p>It is also fair to say that this site is indicative of early-mid-career crises of sorts brought on by other factors such as post-tenure malaise and serious reflections about what we are doing with our limited time in the aftermath of the global COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>In fact, the initial idea for the blog emerged during the height of the pandemic in a long email thread between Jon and Jake. In a somewhat typical exchange, Jake was asking Jon to explain a relatively complex statistical topic (e.g., latent variable modeling in SEM vs.&nbsp;multilevel modeling). Jon was sharing resources, summarizing debates, and explaining issues that have been published on the topic across disparate statistical literatures over the years. Jake thought putting these types of discussions into a blog might be beneficial for multiple reasons. First, rather than burying this writing in emails, others might also appreciate such reviews or tutorials if they were available in a free, public-facing blog. Second, Jon seemed reluctant to write traditional academic articles on such topics since, from his perspective, they would be redundant - the reviews and debates are already out there, you just need to go read them (often in other fields). Meanwhile, Jon was receptive to the idea of a blog; he thought Jake should write more, and a blog might be a good way for both of them to spill ink and “try out” ideas under a critical public eye while perhaps even helping some students and colleagues along the way. So, here we are.</p>
<!-- See about page. Also mention perceived need in our field. See McElreath tweet about cultural anthro. -->
</section>
<section id="how-we-were-inspired-by-charles" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-we-were-inspired-by-charles">How we were inspired by Charles</h2>
<p>The name of our site pays homage to our late mentor and friend, Dr.&nbsp;Charles R. Tittle. It is meant to be a cheeky reference to his chapter entitled “Reflections of a Reluctant but Committed Criminologist” in Gilbert Geis and Mary Dodge’s <a href="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/edit/10.4324/9781315721507/lessons-criminology-gilbert-geis-mary-dodge"><em>Lessons of Criminology</em></a> (pp.23-45).</p>
<p>This is one of our favorite pieces written by Charles. Our perspectives on the field of criminology and criminal justice were heavily shaped by Charles and are thus quite comparable to the views he presents in that chapter. Here is how that chapter starts (p.23):</p>
<!-- Why not just use block quote? -->
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I didn’t intend to become a criminologist. Rather, happenstance led me to investigate certain sociological problems that resulted in my being labeled a criminologist (Tittle, 1991). After a while the reactions of others had the effects that symbolic interactionist theory would predict - I began to think of myself as a criminologist, although one with a larger allegiance. In fact, one of the first conclusions I drew as a criminologist is that criminology ought not be thought of as a discipline. Disciplines have unifying perspectives; criminology does not. Criminology is an umbrella term encompassing diverse studies of crime and crime-relevant phenomena undertaken from many disciplinary points of view. It makes sense to speak of an economic perspective, a political perspective, a historical perspective, or a sociological perspective. It makes no sense to speak of a criminological, a criminal justice, or a criminal perspective (at least not in an academic context). In my mind, the best criminology is done by those with a firm grounding in some discipline, or by those with an appreciation of several different disciplines, the insights of which are then brought to bear on criminological issues.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The chapter then proceeds to introduce several lessons that Charles learned throughout his illustrious career, which he later summarized as follows (pp.40-41):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol type="1">
<li>Criminology is not a discipline but a topical area dependent on a variety of disciplines and that criminological knowledge is best pursued and dispensed within the context of a liberal arts education</li>
<li>Our methods of identifying and recruiting new scholars must be improved</li>
<li>Evidence concerning most important issues having to do with crime and crime-relevant phenomena is weak; success requires that we commit ourselves to a long-range mission of improving that situation</li>
<li>Things are more complicated than our extant theories show, calling for improved theories specifying contingent and interactive effects</li>
<li>The most effective criminology demands that we be aware of and committed to the goal of developing general explanatory schemes refined through test and feedback</li>
<li>Science is the best model to follow in developing criminological knowledge</li>
<li>Weak science, which is likely to continue to characterize criminology for some time, is hardly a basis for policy</li>
<li>The barriers to, and distractions from, good scientific criminology, especially the widespread practice of ad hoc work and the intrusion of personal biases and larger ideologies, must be countered</li>
<li>Civility within the scholarly community is necessary for maximum collective effort</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>If you are interested in learning more about some of Charles Tittle’s intellectual contributions, check out <a href="../../blog-posts/[3]/charles-memorial.html">our blog post on the topic</a>, which contains comments delivered in a tribute panel for Charles at the 2021 American Society of Criminology annual meetings. To be clear, as we also note on our <a href="../../about.html"><em>About</em> page</a>, we were inspired by Charles but he did not endorse this project in any way; in fact, he likely would have thought it was a waste of time better spent contributing in more traditional ways to scientific theory development and testing. We think it’s safe to say that we are both more “reluctant” and less “committed” criminologists than Charles was.</p>
</section>
<section id="but-really-why-are-we-doing-this" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="but-really-why-are-we-doing-this">But really, why are we doing this?</h2>
<p>If we have a loftier aim for our site, it is to answer the call expressed in Charles’ lessons above by contributing modestly to the advancement of scientific criminology. In other words, this site is an attempt to help improve upon, even if just a little, what we perceive are systemic shortcomings in our respective fields.</p>
<p>Of course, we are not alone - scholars raise similar concerns in other social scientific disciplines, including <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.2466/pr0.1990.66.1.195">psychology</a>, <a href="https://openmkt.org/blog/2022/replications-in-marketing-myth-and-reality/">marketing</a>, and <a href="https://elevanth.org/blog/2022/09/19/the-problem-with-cultural-evolution/">evolutionary anthropology</a> to name a few. Likewise, we benefit immensely from the contributions in blogs and bookdown projects shared freely for the collective good by so many people from various disciplinary perspectives working within and outside academia. We encourage you to check out our <a href="../../blog-posts/[2]/favorite_links.html">favorite links</a> post for some excellent examples. Our hope is that this site might offer a comparable (derivative, bargain-basement) version that enriches conversations in our fields about how we can collectively strengthen our science through concerted efforts to improve our theories and the methods we use to generate knowledge about them.</p>
<p>In our own academic careers and scholarly pursuits, we continually try to improve our understanding of philosophies of science, substantive theories of crime and deviance, and quantitative methods used to test social scientific theories. Rather than solely bothering seemingly uninterested authors about these issues in the reviews we write for journals (we both now sign our reviews but the editors often take our names off), we thought we might as well put our thoughts out in public and subject them to criticism. Of course, we recognize the most likely outcome is that our thoughts, like in many of the reviews we write, will simply be (justifiably?) ignored. But we expect our own thinking on these matters will be strengthened by forcing ourselves to write them down and, ideally, by then accounting for your feedback.</p>
<p>So welcome to our blog! We’ll try to keep the navel gazing to a minimum from here on out.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{brauerandjakeday2023,
  author = {Jon Brauer and Jake Day},
  title = {Welcome to the Reluctant Criminologists},
  date = {2023-03-10},
  url = {https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/welcome-blog.html},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-brauerandjakeday2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jon Brauer and Jake Day. 2023. <span>“Welcome to the Reluctant
Criminologists.”</span> March 10, 2023. <a href="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/welcome-blog.html">https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/welcome-blog.html</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>general</category>
  <guid>https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[1]/welcome-blog.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.reluctantcriminologists.com/blog-posts/[1]/RC_logo_white.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
